<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Catholike and ecclesiasticall exposition vppon the epistle of S. Iude the apostle collected and gathered out of the workes of the best writers by Augustine Marlorat ... ; translated out of Latin into Englishe ... by I.D. mynister.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17406.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4778</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23878001</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23878001</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26942</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06987)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26942)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1836:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Catholike and ecclesiasticall exposition vppon the epistle of S. Iude the apostle collected and gathered out of the workes of the best writers by Augustine Marlorat ... ; translated out of Latin into Englishe ... by I.D. mynister.</title>
                  <author>Marlorat, Augustin, 1506-1562.</author>
                  <author>I. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 37 [i.e. 76], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Gerard Dewes and Henry Marshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁸ E⁷.</note>
                  <note>Pages numbered on recto only.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped and stained, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Jude --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26942:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26942:1"/>
            <p>A CATHOLIKE and eccleſiaſticall expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition vppon the epiſtle of S. Iude the Apoſtle: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> COLLECTED AND GA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the workes of the beſt writers by Auguſtine Marlorat, that moſt notable and excellent Diuine: ¶ TRANSLATED OVT OF Latin into Engliſhe, for the behoofe of the vnlearned in the ſame tongue: both for the better increaſe of their knowledge and fayth in the true worſhip &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, as alſo for the better framing of their liues &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation according to the ſame; By <hi>I. D.</hi> Myniſter.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn the 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>39. Search the ſcriptures: for in them yee thinke to haue eternall life, and they are they which teſtifie of mee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> AT LONDON BY</hi> Gerard Dewes, and Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Marſhe. 1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26942:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26942:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing it is moſt true (good Chriſtian reader) that the holy and ſacred ſcripture contayneth in it milke for children, &amp; ſtronger mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes for men of more firme ſtomackes: and is by ſainte Gregory very fitly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a broad and great riuer, wherein a Lambe may wade ſafely, and the Elephant ſwimme ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently: meaning by the Lambe (as himſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth) the ſimple and vnlearned, and by the Elephant, ſuch as are mighty in the ſcriptures: And whereas our ſauiour himſelfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth, that all which looke for eternall lyfe, ſhould ſearch the ſcriptures: I cannot but maruaile at the mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous blindnes, or rather madnes of the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Chriſte, the Papiſtes, which barre the lay people from ſo great a benefit as the reading of the ſcriptures: affirming and moſt blaſphemouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendinge, that Images ought to be bookes for the vnlearned, and callinge blindnes the mother of deuotion: abuſing alſo the ſcripture, ſaying. <hi>Giue not that which is holy vnto dogges, neither caſt your pearles before ſwyne:</hi> meaninge by
<pb facs="tcp:26942:3"/>
dogges and ſwyne, the lay people. In which their groſſe poſitions, falſe aſſertions, blinde errours and blaſphemyes, they ſhew how hart-blinde &amp; hard-harted they are, ſo wilfully &amp; malitiouſly to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and gaine ſay the true and eternall wyſdome and counſaile of the ſonne of God. But all true Chriſtians, whoſe heartes God by his holy ſpirite hath illuminated, haue learned a newe leſſon, though taught ſince the beginning in the ſchoole of Chriſte: and that is, to reſorte to the hearing, and reading of the ſcripture, as to the onely true and eternall touchſtone, able to try and examine the droſſe and baſe metall of ſinne and falſhoode from that pure golde and moſt currant coyne of righteouſnes and truth: and ſo ſeeing the baſenes and vileneſſe of them ſelues and their own works, indeauoure to put of their olde man, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge their owne vnrighteouſnes being but droſſe for the righteouſneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, being as the moſt pure and fineſt golde. And if at any time they bee toſſed with a tempeſt in the darke nighte of ſpirituall blindnes, vppon the ſea of ſin ready to ſwallow them vp, they runne to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion and repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance as to a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe: they caſt the Anker of hope, &amp; take faſt holde in Gods mercifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: they haue an eye to Chriſte Ieſus as to the Load-ſtarre which muſt lead them to the hauen of lyfe and ſaluation. But the wicked and ſtagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:26942:3"/>
Papiſtes are otherwiſe affected and afflicted: for they are toſſed, <hi>Inter ſpem curamque timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res inter &amp; iras.</hi> Betwene an vncertaine hope and a ſeruile feare, a daſtardly deſperatneſſe or a blinde foole-hardines. Thou ſeeſt in briefe (chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reader) the Papiſtes vaine opinion, and the true meaning of Chryſtians, concerning the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or not readinge of ſcriptures, &amp; the effectes of both: it ſhoulde ſeeme therefore needeleſſe to perſwade any to reade the ſcriptures, whereas all (that regard their own ſaluation) are throughly perſwaded in their conſcience to the ſame: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge, it were good for the farther eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of this pointe of doctrine, to haue alwaies before our eyes the enſample of the Eunuche in the eight of the actes: who being an heathen, was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to chriſtianity by reading the ſcripture, God ſending vnto him Phillip to deuide the word (which hee red) rightly vnto him. God hath ſent vnto vs many Phillips, ô howe thankefull ought wee to bee for the ſame. The Eunuche read the ſcriptures as hee rode in a Wagon, let vs reade them ſitting euery man vnder his vyne and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his figge tree.</p>
            <p>This our Apoſtle gaue all dilligence to write vnto vs of our common ſaluation: let vs not bee too negligent in neglecting euery one his owne ſaluation. The holy ſpirite hath deſcended longe
<pb facs="tcp:26942:4"/>
ſince in fiery &amp; clouen tongues, &amp; euery one hath heard him ſpeake in his mother tongue: let vs not ſtop our eares like the deafe Adder which refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to heare the voyce of the charmer charme hee neuer ſo wiſely.</p>
            <p>And as touching this parte of ſcripture which followeth with an expoſition on the ſame, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth very lyuely our preſent times: the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition thereof is learned and true; the tranſlation into our tongue faithfully done, and I pray God it may bee as fruitfully vnderſtoode and followed: which is and was the ende of the writing &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating thereof: which ende being attayned, wee ſhall all with one minde and one mouth prayſe God, the firſt beginner and the laſt fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher of our fayth and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Giue the glory to God alone.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="works_cited">
            <pb facs="tcp:26942:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE NAMES of the Authors, out of</hi> whoſe workes this expoſition is col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and the letters capitoll, whereby their names are to bee knowne in the reading of the ſame <hi>Marked thus.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>B. Bullinger,</item>
               <item>M. Martin Luther.</item>
               <item>I. Imlerus.</item>
               <item>C. I. Caluin.</item>
               <item>L. L. Pelycane.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26942:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26942:5"/>
            <head>AVGVSTINE Marlorat vppon the <hi>Epistle of S. Iude.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vdas</hi> (whom <hi>Mathew</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Lebbeus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bulling.</note> whoſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name was <hi>Thaddeus</hi>) is ſayde to bee the brother of <hi>Iames</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of <hi>Alphee,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Symon</hi> the Cananite,<note place="margin">M. Luth.</note> 
                  <hi>M.</hi> whoſe mother was <hi>Mary Iacoby</hi> or <hi>Cleophas,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Mary</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother of Chriſt, as we reade, <hi>Marke, 6.</hi> verſ. <hi>3.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
                  <hi>C.</hi> But foraſmuch as of this epiſtle alſo of <hi>S. Iude,</hi> there hath bene no litle ado among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> learned au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient wryters, which haue bene in diuerſe opinions touching the ſame, yet becauſe it is very neceſſary and profitable to be red, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in it nothing at al, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth either ſwarue or decline from the purity &amp; ſimplicity of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike doctrine: and ſith now long ſithens this epiſtle hath bin in price and authority amongeſt the beſt and godlieſt writers, wee doe gladly and willingly recken this for one amonge the reſt of the epiſtles Canonicall. <hi>B.</hi> As touching the lyfe of this holy man <hi>Iude</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bulling.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26942:8"/>
(if <hi>Euſebius</hi> is to be credited and belieued, cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and alleaging <hi>Hegeſyppus</hi> for his author) hee lyued in the Emperoure <hi>Domitians</hi> tyme fewe yeares after that the Apoſtles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord were taken away. Who lyuing in a moſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted time, &amp; foreſeeing by the ſpyrite what would come to paſſe hereafter, wrote this epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: which becauſe it is ſo briefe, &amp; ſo ſhort as of it ſelfe needeth noe longe or great argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the totall ſome whereof doth agree almoſt with the <hi>2.</hi> chap. of the latter epiſtle of ſainte <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle. And for becauſe there were certayne wicked varlets and vngodly perſons craftely crepte in amonge the profeſſors of Chriſtes goſpell, ſhrowding them ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name and tytle of Chriſtianity &amp; chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who tooke it for a great pleaſure to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were yet weake, and not through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtablyſhed and ſetled in the faith, to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane contempt of God: The apoſtle ſainte <hi>Iude</hi> doth here fyrſt declare, that the faithfull ought not to bee troubled or diſmayde with ſuch ſubtile kinde of deuiſes and inuentions, wherewith the church of Chryſte and of God hath alwayes bene aſſaulted.<note place="margin">Imlerus.</note> 
                  <hi>I</hi> And therefore this ought not to ſeeme ſtraunge. Whereas now longe agoe the faythfull for this cauſe and for this intente haue bene fore appointed,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26942:8"/>
and predeſtinated: and it hath ben foretolde by the Apoſtles that ſuch kinde of men will craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely and vnwares creepe in amonge the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian flocke.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
                  <hi>C.</hi> To the ende therefore they ſhould be the more circumſpecte, and take di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent &amp; good heede to themſelues to beware of ſuch peſtilent and crafty creepers, he doth oft exhorte them and <hi>B</hi> admoniſh them to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinew and perſeuere in pure and ſincere reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,<note place="margin">Bullinge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> and to declare and ſhew forth the verity and truth of the goſpell by good workes.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>C.</hi> But to the intent he may make theſe craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and falſe deceauers the more to be hated,<note place="margin">Aug. Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and alſo to be abhorred and ſhunned, <hi>A</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth at large, not only their manners,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> and their corrupted and wicked deuiſes, <hi>C</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hee doth ſeuerely denounce vnto them the vengeance of God to be at hand, ſuch as theyr impiety and vngodlineſſe doth deſerue.<note place="margin">Bullinger</note> 
                  <hi>B.</hi> But many things for the moſt parte are taken out of the latter epiſtle of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> as wee ſayd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen now. Neyther verely ought that to ſeeme ſtraunge or newes to any man: for wee ſee euen the latter Prophets to haue red the bookes and ſentences of the firſt: yea, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes to vſe them, and to tranſferre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſentences and wordes of theirs into their owne writing, The things therefore that are
<pb facs="tcp:26942:7"/>
here briefly touched, are handled more at large in the epiſtle of <hi>S. Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Caluin.</note>
                  <hi>C.</hi> Now if wee weigh &amp; conſider diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what Satan goeth aboute to doe in this our age alſo, ſithence the renewing and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againe of the goſpell, and what ſleights and ſubtile deuiſes hee doth practize &amp; ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to ouerthrowe, and cleane to ſubuert the fayth and feare of God, the admonitions and inſtructions that were profitable in <hi>Iude</hi> his time, the ſame in theſe our dayes are much more neceſſary. But all theſe things we ſhall the better learne by reading of this epiſtle.</p>
            </argument>
            <head>THE TEXT.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. 1.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vdas the ſeruant of Ieſus Chriſt</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Imlerus. Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>Iudas</hi> beginneth his epiſtle afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Apoſtles. <hi>C.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> calleth himſelfe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> name is common to all the god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> myxed one with another; but hee calleth hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelfe ſo in reſpect of his Apoſtleſhip; for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are properly and peculiarly iudged to bee th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeruantes of Chriſte, to whom he hath inio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned any publique offyce or function: So th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now wee knowe to what ende the Apoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are accuſtomed to ſet forth them ſelues wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:26942:7"/>
this tytle. Raſhly therefore doth he preſume, whoſoeuer he be, that taketh vpon him the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and authority of teaching, that is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully thereunto called. The callinge therefore of the Apoſtles is their ſufficient teſtimony, becauſe they intrude not them ſelues into the offyce of teaching, by their owne priuate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and iudgement. Neither is this ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent inough of it ſelfe to be placed in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, vnleſſe they behaue them ſelues faythfully therein. Which then verely they ſhall doe: Firſt, if they declare that God is the author of their function and calling wherein they are placed: Secondly, if they execute the ſame faythfully according as they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded. But becauſe many doe counterfayte this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, namely, that they are the ſeruauntes of Chryſt, and falſly bragge them ſelues to bee that, from the which they are farre wyde, wee muſt alwayes take good heede, and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the thinge it ſelfe be anſwerable to their profeſſion or not.<note place="margin">Aug. Mar. Philipp. 3. verſ. 18.19.</note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> For that is moſt true that the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paule</hi> wryteth: <hi>Many walke, that are the ennemyes of the Croſſe of Chriſt, whoſe ende is destruction, whoſe God is their belly, and glory to theyr ſhame: which minde earthly thinges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It followeth in the texte. <hi>The brother of
<pb facs="tcp:26942:6"/>
Iames] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Becauſe there were many <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ullinger</note> therefore hee addeth this to put a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwene him and other that were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led after the ſame name.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> Hee addeth to alſo his name, becauſe it was ſo famous, and ſo well knowne of the churches: for although the doctrine and authority of fayth depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon no mortall man, yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding this is a great ſtrengthning and ſetting for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of fayth, when the integrity and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of the man, that taketh vpon him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of a teacher, is wel &amp; ſufficiently knowne vnto vs. Moreouer, the authority of <hi>Iames</hi> is not here ſet forth vnder a colour, as of ſome priuate man, but becauſe he was counted one of the cheifeſt Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Galla. 2. verſ. 9.</note> among al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churches.</p>
            <p>Thus haſt thou both the author of this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, and alſo the ſubſcription. Nowe it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth to declare to whom hee wrought this epiſtle.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>To them which are called] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> By this word <hi>(called)</hi> he ſignifieth all the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe the Lord hath ſeuered them to him ſelfe. But becauſe this worde <hi>(calling)</hi> is nothing els then the effecte of the eternall election, it is ſome times taken for election it ſelfe. Heere in this place it maketh no great matter if thou take it both wayes. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, hee commendeth the grace of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26942:6"/>
God wherewith hee vouchedſafe to make his choyce of them, to bee of his flocke and folde. He ſignifieth alſo,<note place="margin">Aug. Mar. Ihon. 4.19.</note> that men cannot preuent God, neither can they come vnto him at any time, till he drawe them. <hi>A. For hee loued vs firſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 65.1.</note> 
               <hi>And hee is dayly found of them that ſought him not: and appeareth vnto them which asked not after him.</hi> It followeth.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſanctified in God the father] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> The ſence and meaninge of this is: that they that are called being wicked and vngodly in them ſelues,<note place="margin">Bullinger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phe. 2.3.</note> haue their full ſanctification in &amp; from God. <hi>B. For wee are all by nature the children of wrath, and vyle bondſlaues to Satan. But God taking pity vpon vs, ſent his ſonne into the world, which loued vs, and waſhed vs from our ſinnes in his owne bloude.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluin. Aug. Mar.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> All they therefore are ſanctified, whom God hath regenerated by his ſpirite, <hi>A.</hi> and grafted into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of his ſonne Chryſte by fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And preſerued in Ieſus</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore he addeth that we are kept and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in Chriſte:<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> for Satan euery minute &amp; moment of an houre ſyeth alwayes in wayte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſnatch vs vp as it were for a Pray, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erly to deſtroy vs, had not Chryſte our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur protected and defended vs, whom the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her hath appoynted to bee our keeper and
<pb facs="tcp:26942:9"/>
watchman, for this purpoſe, that nothing bee loſt, that hee hath receaued into his tuition &amp; ſafe keping.<note place="margin">Aug. Mar. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hon. 6.39.</note> 
               <hi>A. For this is the will of my Father that ſent mee, that of all that he hath geuen me, I ſhall loſe nothing, but rayſe it vp agayne at the last daye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hon. 10.27.</note> And againe: <hi>My ſheepe heare my voyce, and I knowe them, and they followe mee, and I geue vnto them, eternall lyfe, and they ſhall neuer periſhe, neyther ſhall any man plucke them out of my hande. My Father which gaue them mee, is greater then all, and no man is able to take them out of my Fathers hand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ihon. 17.12.</note> Alſo, <hi>Thoſe that thou gauest mee, haue I kept, and none of them is lost, but that lost chylde, that the ſcripture myght bee fulfilled. C.</hi> A threefold benefite of God therefore in all <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the Godly doth <hi>Iudas</hi> heere declare.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that by theyr callinge, hee hath made them partakers of the goſpell. Secondly, that by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> his ſpyrite hee hath regenerated them into newneſſe of lyfe. And thirdely, that by the power of Chriſte, hee hath kept them, that they ſhoulde not fall away from ſaluation.<note place="margin">Aug. Mar.</note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> To this agreeth that ſayinge of <hi>S. Peter</hi> in his <hi>1.</hi> epiſtle verſ. <hi>5. Wee are kept by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God through faith vnto ſaluation, which is prepared for this purpoſe, ready to bee ſhewe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the laſt time.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bullinger</note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> In theſe three members
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26942:9"/>
therefore thou haſt the whole ſumme of the goſpell, which <hi>Paule</hi> eſpecially mingleth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the titles or inſcriptions of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercy bee vnto you, and peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> verſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Bullin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bee multiplied.] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> This is an holy wyſhe, and a very Apoſtolike ſalutation.</p>
            <p>Hee deſireth three thinges to bee multiplied and increaſed (that to is ſay) <hi>Mercy, Peace, and Charity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> This worde <hi>(Mercy)</hi> is as much in effect almoſt, as <hi>Grace,</hi> in <hi>Paules</hi> ſalutations. If a man will haue a more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till or fine difference: properly, grace is the effecte of mercy. Becauſe God doth imbrace vs with his loue, for no other cauſe, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee beholdeth our myſeries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.</hi> This mercy the Father of heauen doth increaſe in vs,<note place="margin">Bullin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> when hee taketh pitty vppon vs, and forgeueth vs our ſinnes, and doth as it were power downe him ſelfe and all his benefittes vppon vs day by day, moſt lybe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and bountifully: ſo that hee doth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes, and euer nowe and then, knitte as it were, and bynde him ſelfe more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and neerely vnto vs by his beneuolence, and fatherly benignity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26942:12"/>This worde <hi>(peace)</hi> doth ſignifie the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity or quietneſſe of the minde or conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; the deſire or ſtuddy of vnity and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord with all men. <hi>Charity</hi>] It may bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode as well of God towards men, as of one man towardes another. If it be vnderſtoode of God, then the ſence is, that he would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, to increaſe the ſame amonge men, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the truſt and confidence of his heauenly loue may dayly more and more bee confirmed and ſtabliſhed in our heartes: if of men, it is not amyſſe neyther, that the ſame God alſo, will vouchſafe to kindle and confirme in them mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall loue and charity one towardes another, <hi>I.</hi> that they may bee of one minde and of one accorde,<note place="margin">Ierus.</note> and to continew helpfull and benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall one towardes another.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. <hi>Beloued, when I gaue all dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to write vnto you of the common ſaluation, it was needefull for mee to wryte vnto you to exhorte you that yee ſhould earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contend for the fayth which was once geuen vnto the ſainctes.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> texte.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>llinger</note>
               <hi>Beloued when I gaue all diligence] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Here hee ſheweth the cauſe that enforced him to write, indeuouringe to get theyr good will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26942:12"/>
and fauoure, ſhewinge with (all as by a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face) the ſcope &amp; drift of thoſe things whereof hee mindeth to ſpeake.<note place="margin">Mar. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>M.</hi> Some doe thinke that a certayne earneſt and vehement deſire was the cauſe that inforced <hi>Iudas</hi> to write, as wee are wonte to ſay of them that doe euen burne as it were with ſome earneſt affection or other, that they cannot moderate or wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde themſelues, but needes they muſt doe this or that: So that it was neceſſity in him after their opinion, that the earneſt deſire that <hi>Iudas</hi> had to write would not ſuffer him to keepe ſilence.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> But if a man examine the matter more narrowly, hee ſhall ſee here two diſtincte members, that whereas otherwiſe, hee was ready inough, and earneſtly bent, yet neceſſity hath alſo compelled him to wryte.</p>
            <p>Hee ſignifieth therefore that hee was willing verely, and very deſirous to write vnto them, and yet notwithſtanding compelled ſo to doe of neceſſity: for (as it followeth in the texte) being aſſaulted of the wicked, they were to be inſtructed, to prepare and addreſſe themſelues to the battell. In this firſt place therefore <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> declareth that hee had ſo great care for their health and ſaluation, that hee wiſhed to write of his owne accord, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> very earneſtly. Then, to the intent to ſtyrre them vp to geue
<pb facs="tcp:26942:11"/>
the more heede &amp; attention, hee ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo it ſelfe required ſo to doe, for neceſſity is a ſharpe ſpurre. Except they had ben fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned how neceſſary this exhortation was for them, they would haply haue bene ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what negligent and ſlouthfull in the reading of the ſame. But when hee declared in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninge, that hee wrote vppon preſent neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, it is all one, as if hee had ſtricken vp the alarame, to rouſe them vp out of their drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſleepe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Mar.</note> and careleſſe ſecurity. <hi>A. Paule</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame maner ſtyrreth vp the <hi>Philippians</hi> to take heede to them ſelues, and to beware of falſe Apoſtles and deceauers.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilip. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>It grieueth mee not</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>to write the ſame things oft to you, for to you it is a ſure thinge: Beware of dogges, beware of euill workers, beware of Conciſion.</hi> It followeth. <hi>Of the common ſaluation] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Some bookes haue <hi>(yours)</hi> but amyſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uin.</note> For hee maketh ſaluation to bee common as well to other as to him ſelfe. Whereby it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe that the credit and eſtimation of the doctrine of ſaluation is not a litle fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug. Mar.</note> when a man ſpeaketh of his owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; experience. <hi>A.</hi> For it will bee counted but a fooliſh bablinge, to reaſon and diſpute of ſaluation amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g others, whereof we our ſelues haue had no taſte or feeling at all. A doctor of experience therefore (if we may
<pb facs="tcp:26942:11"/>
ſo ſpeake) <hi>Iudas</hi> profeſſeth himſelfe to bee, when hee reckeneth himſelfe amonge the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to bee partaker of the ſame fellowſhip of ſaluation with them. And truely if there bee but on faith of all the faithfull beleeuers, one goſpell, one <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſte,</hi> keeper and defendour of the flocke, then muſt ſaluation of neceſſity be a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon thinge to them al. For the ende of our Chriſtian faith, is the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſoules. <hi>1.</hi> epiſtle of <hi>Peter, 1.</hi> verſ. <hi>9.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> verſ. 9</note> 
               <hi>To exhort you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yee ſhould earneſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for the fayth] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> The Greeke word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth ſo much as if he ſhould ſay,<note place="margin">Calu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Exhorting you.</hi> But foraſmuch as he noteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of his purpoſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words are thus to be reſolued: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I might exhort you earneſtly to contend, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your fayth may bee forthered &amp; ſtrengthned. By y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which words hee ſignifieth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in keeping of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith, wee muſt labour with all our might, &amp; withſtand ſtrongly the contrary aſſaultes of Satan: For hee admoniſheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to perſeuere and continew in the faith, for that many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts and battayles are lyke to enſue.<note place="margin">Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> For the great multitude of deceauers, doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goe about to weaken &amp; make feeble by all meanes poſſible they may, the faith of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly, but vtterly to ſubuerte it, and ouerthrowe it. Wherefore, they that are once called to the fayth haue neede not a litle to bee carefull,
<pb facs="tcp:26942:10"/>
that they may perſeuere and continew therein ſounde and perfect to the ende. It followeth. <hi>Which was once geuen to the ſaincts]</hi> This hee addeth, that they may know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fayth is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to this ende, &amp; vppon this condition, that they ſhoulde not faynte at any tyme, or fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from it.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g. Mar.</note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> Hee calleth the faythfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers <hi>(Saintes)</hi> after the vſuall manner of the ſcripture, which are ſanctified by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloude and ſpirite of Chriſte.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4 <hi>For there are certayne vngodly men craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely crept in,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e texte.</note> 
               <hi>which were before of olde booked or billed to this condemnation, turning the grace of God vnto wantones: and denying God which is th'only Lord, and our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For there are certaine vngodly men crafte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crept in] <hi>A.</hi>
               </hi> Hee rendereth the cauſe why hee could not forbeare,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug. Mar.</note> but needes muſt write vnto them.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lerus.</note> 
               <hi>I.</hi> In this hee doth immitate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles, who haue written many things of falſe Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug. Mar.</note> and deceauers. <hi>A.</hi> To this ende verely that the faythfull ſhould bee care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and watchfull for their owne ſaluation, leaſt by any meanes they ſhoulde bee carryed away from the ſimplicity of Gods woorde,
<pb facs="tcp:26942:10"/>
and from the receaued fayth in Chryſt.<note place="margin">Calu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>C</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Satan be alwayes a mortall enemy to the godly, and ceaſeth not euer nowe and then to egge and pricke them forwarde to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit wickedneſſe: yet notwithſtandinge <hi>Iudas</hi> doth admonyſhe them, to whom hee writeth of the preſent neceſſity. Nowe ſpecially (ſaith hee) doth Satan in deede enter and ſet vppon you: arme your ſelues therefore to reſiſt him.<note place="margin">L. Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cane.</note> 
               <hi>L</hi> Now come falſe teachers &amp; are euen alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy entred, which will eaſely ſeduce you vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, if you take not good heede.<note place="margin">Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>A</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would warne you in time that yee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinew in the fayth which yee haue heard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>C.</hi> Hence we may gather that it is the duety &amp; parte of a good &amp; faythfull paſtour diligently and prudently to looke about him,<note place="margin">Calui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate and condition of the church doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre, and accordingly to imploy his diligence of teaching and inſtructing. But euery word carrieth with it his ſubſtaunce and weight. For this worde, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, doth notifie an indirect or priuy kinde of craftines, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters of Satan deceaue the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that foreſeed not things to come. For in the nighte time when men are a ſleepe, Satan ſoweth and ſcattereth abroade his Darnell &amp; Tares, to corrupt &amp; marre the pure &amp; cleane
<pb facs="tcp:26942:13"/>
ſeede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords word.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itt. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Mat. 13.</hi> verſ. <hi>25.</hi> And withal teacheth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is a priuy &amp; an inward miſchiefe full of ſecret hatred &amp; mallice. For here alſo is the craftines &amp; ſubtlety of Satan eſpied to ſtyrre vp thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flocke to be enemies, they that may with more facility de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llinger</note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> Hee noteth therefore the cunninge and crafty deceipt of theſe Satanicall decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, which in no wiſe will ſeeme to bee ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to truth and piety, but vnder a colour &amp; cloake rather of truth and piety, they brag and vaunte of them ſelues. Of ſuch kinde of men as theſe bee, <hi>S. Peter</hi> in his <hi>2.</hi> epiſt. <hi>2.</hi> verſ. <hi>1.</hi> ſpeaketh thus: <hi>There were falſe Prophets alſo among the people, euen as there ſhalbe falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers among you, which priuily ſhall brynge in damnable hereſies, euen denying the Lord that hath bought them, and bring vppon them ſelues ſwyft damnation. A. Paule</hi> alſo of falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles writeth in this ſorte.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11. verſ. 13.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>For ſuch falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, are deceiptfull workers, tranſformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Apoſtles of Chriſte, and no meruayle, for Satan him ſelfe is tranſformed into an angell of lyghte: therefore it is no great thinge, if that his miniſters alſo bee tranſformed as the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of righteouſneſſe.</hi> Alſo Chriſte him ſelfe hath deſcrybed them in this maner.<note place="margin">Matt. 7. verſ. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of falſe Prophetes which come to you in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26942:13"/>
ſheepes clothinge, but inwardly they are rauening Woulfes, yee ſhall know them by their fruites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It followeth. <hi>Which were before boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluin</note> 
               <hi>or ordayned to this iudgment] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> He calleth it iudgment or condemnation, becauſe they corrupted the doctrine of piety, which no man can doe without his owne deſtruction. Furthermore, herehence this metaphor is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternall counſayle of God, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which the faythfull are ordeyned to ſaluation, is called a booke. But when the faithfull doe heare thoſe falſe Prophets to be appointed to eternall death, they ought to take the more heede, leaſt they alſo wrap them ſelues in the ſame deſtruction with them. Howbeit <hi>Iudas</hi> would therewithall preuent al daunger, leaſt happely the newneſſe or ſtraungnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing ſhould trouble or ouerthrow ſome of them. <hi>L.</hi> As who woulde ſay, leaſt this thinge,<note place="margin">L. Pely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane.</note> as ſtrange or neuer heard or knowne of before, might trouble your mindes, know yee that it was long ſince thus decreed by the ſecert coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of God, thus it hath bene foretold, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhoulde ſome aryſe, which with theyr wicked deedes, ſhould both try &amp; exercyſe your piety &amp; godlines, bringing vppon them ſelues ſwyfte da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. Herehence therefore we may learne, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church is not exerciſed &amp; tried but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26942:14"/>
determinate counſell of God. It followeth. <hi>Whych tourne the grace of our God vnto wantonnes]</hi> Now hee declareth manyfeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and clearely, what maner of miſchife y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, that they ſhould beware &amp; take heede of: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this: that theſe falſe Apoſtles &amp; deceauers, abuſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God vnto all wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tonnes &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſnes, thinkinge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> becauſe their ſinnes were forgeuen, they might doe what they liſt. They ſinned therefore without all ſhame, and willingly fell backe againe into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlauery and bondage of ſinne, from whence Chriſt had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed them by the ſhedding of his bloude. <hi>C.</hi> The grace of God verely appeared to a far other end,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> then to geue men leaue to ſinne, as <hi>Paule</hi> plainely witneſſeth, ſayinge: <hi>The grace of God hath appeared healthfull to all men, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs, that denying vngodlynes, and worldly lustes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. to Tit. 2. verſ. 11.</note> 
               <hi>wee ſhoulde lyue ſoberly, and righteouſly, and godly in this preſent euyll worlde.</hi> Let vs know therefore, that there is nothinge more hurtfull &amp; pernitious then theſe kinde of men, which of the grace of Chriſte, doe take an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to liue wantonly and licentiouſly. And becauſe wee teach, that wee are ſaued by the free mercy of God, the Papiſts lay this to our charge as a greate faulte. But what doth it preuaile with wordes to confute their ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſnes,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26942:14"/>
ſith euery where &amp; in all places we call earneſtly vpon repentance, the feare of God, &amp; newnes of life. They themſelues doe not only corrupt &amp; marre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole world by their euill examples &amp; wicked life, but alſo take quite out of the world by their peſtiferous and wicked doctrine, true holines, and the pure worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and ſeruing of God.<note place="margin">Mar. Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>M.</hi> In deede they call them ſelues chriſtians, and brag much of the goſpell, but they liue ſuch a kinde of life, as they doe whatſoeuer pleaſeth them, ſinning moſt wickedly and abhominably in dronken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in lechery, and all abhomination. Their Byſſhops and Prelates doe vaunte and ſay, wee haue taken vpon vs, not a worldly, but a ſpirituall ſtate and condition of life: vnder which name &amp; falſe pretence,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> they haue gotten great treaſures, pleaſures, and dignities: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee may rather thinke them to bee like the <hi>Lybertines</hi> of our time, of whom <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> ſpeaketh, as it ſhall more clearely appeare in the diſcourſe hereof. It followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And God which is the only Lord]</hi> Certaine old tranſlations haue, <hi>Chriſt which is the only God &amp; Lorde.</hi> In the epiſtle of <hi>S. Peter</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made onely of Chriſte, and there hee is called Lord. For thus he writeth,<note place="margin">2. Peter. 2. verſ. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Euen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyinge the Lorde which hath boughte them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26942:15"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. Mar.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> If any man thinke it better to reade it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctiuely or by it ſelfe, then the ſence will be, <hi>Chiefly they deny God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> 
               <hi>L</hi> whom once they haue profeſſed, which is the only Lord of all things, both in heauen and earth. It followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aluin.</note>
               <hi>And deny our Lord Ieſus Chriſte] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Hee vnderſtandeth Chriſte to be denyed, when ſuch as haue bene redeemed by his bloud, haue ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them ſelues againe to bee bondſlaues to Satan, makinge as much as in them lyeth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable and ineſtimable benefite &amp; price of our redemption, to be fruſtrate &amp; of none effect. Therefore let vs remember y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte dyed and roſe againe for vs, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end he might make vs a peculiar people to him ſelfe, &amp; that he might be Lord of our lyfe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug. Mar.</note> and death. <hi>A.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, Chriſte is denied, when wee derogate from him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is his owne: After which maner the Monks, and ſuch like deny Chriſt. <hi>M.</hi> For when they preach that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happineſſe &amp; felicity,<note place="margin">Mar. Lut.</note> is to faſt, to gad &amp; wander on pylgrimage, to builde Churches, and Monaſteries: to vowe chaſtity, obedience, pouerty, and ſuch like: they plainely deceaue the ſimple and ignorante by their works, but of Chriſte they make no mention at all: which is as much, as if they ſhoulde ſay, it is very needeful and neceſſary for thee to deſerue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26942:15"/>
by thy owne good workes, Chriſte profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thee nothing, his works cannot help thee: and ſo they deny the Lorde, who hath boughte vs with his bloude.</p>
            <p>The Heretickes alſo that deſtroy eyther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> humanity or deity of Chriſte, are ſayd to deny him, as it may appeare in the <hi>1.</hi> of <hi>Ihon, 2.</hi> the <hi>22.</hi> verſ. and in the ſame epiſtle the <hi>4.</hi> chapter the <hi>3.</hi> verſ.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5. <hi>My minde is therefore to put you in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance hereof,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The text<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>foraſmuch as yee once know this, how that the Lord, after that he had deliuered the people out of Aegypte, deſtroyed them which afterwarde belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My mynde is therefore to put you in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> He declareth by diuers examples,<note place="margin">Bullinger</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not enough for vs to confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are deliuered out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Aegyptian</hi> bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage, that is, out of Satans kingdome, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> freedome &amp; glorious liberty of the goſpell which wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, vnleſſe our life bee anſwerable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. <hi>L.</hi> And except wee perſeuere &amp; continew in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God whereunto wee are called,<note place="margin">L. Pely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane.</note> our deliuerance ſhal profit vs litle.<note place="margin">Bullinger</note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> By al which things he confuteth thoſe ſeducers, and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſaintes of God, to expreſſe the fayth of
<pb facs="tcp:26942:16"/>
Chryſte, by a lyfe worthy of Chriſte, and to be helpers to others, that they follow not the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy examples of theſe ſeducers.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> But he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a litle preface, either for modeſty ſake to excuſe himſelfe, that hee ſeeme not to teach them as being altogether ignorant of things vnknowne; or els truely for ſome greater cauſe of earneſtnes, he confeſſeth that he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vnto them no new thing, or not heard of before, that hee may winne thereby the more credit and authority in that which hee is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſpeake.<note place="margin">Imlerus.</note> 
               <hi>I.</hi> I ſuppoſe (ſaith hee) that it is not needefull for me to teach you, ſith you your ſelues are not ignorant.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> Only I bring to your remembrances, that which yee haue once learned,<note place="margin">L. Pely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane.</note> 
               <hi>L</hi> leaſt that which yee knowe ſlip out of your memories. But as he geueth them knowledge to geue the more heede to be wary and circumſpect, ſo, leaſte they ſhoulde thinke the care that hee toke for them to bee ſuperfluous, hee ſaith that it was needefull for them to bee forewarned. For this is not the vſe of Gods worde only, to learne thoſe things whereof wee haue none experience, but alſo that it may ſtyrre vs vp to the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt meditatinge of thoſe thinges which we haue heretofore learned, and may not ſuffer vs by any meanes, to waxe dull and colde in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26942:16"/>
knowledge. <hi>A.</hi> After this maner,<note place="margin">Aug. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> doth <hi>Paule</hi> exhorte his ſonne <hi>Tymothee,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Preach the worde, bee inſtant in ſeaſon, &amp; out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: improoue, rebuke, exhort in all longe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe and doctryne. 2. Tymo.</hi> Chap. <hi>4.</hi> verſ. <hi>2. C.</hi> But of all that hath bene hetherto ſpoken,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> this is the ſumme: after that wee are called of God, wee muſt not ſecurely brag and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his grace, but rather walke warely in his feare: becauſe if any man doe dally and mocke with God after this ſorte, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of his grace ſhall not eſcape vnpuniſhed And this hee declareth by three examples.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lord when hee had deliuered his people out of the land of Aegypt.]</hi> The firſt example is taken out of the ſeconde booke of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bullinge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> Euen as God in time paſt brought the chyldren of <hi>Iſraëll</hi> out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hard ſeruitude and bondage of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and led them through the middeſt of the red Sea, and through the wyldernes, into the lande of promyſe: euen ſo the very ſame God hath brought vs <hi>(the Lord Chryſte being our guyde &amp; captaine)</hi> out of the ſeruitude and bondage of Satan by the fountaine of regeneration, wherewith he hath waſhed vs from all our ſinnes to eternal lyfe. But as this deliuerance profited the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, which murmured agaynſt God in the deſert,
<pb facs="tcp:26942:17"/>
which defiled them ſelues with Idolatry, with meates offered vp to Idols, with whoredome and glottony (for certaine thowſands of them were ſlayne in the wilderneſſe) euen ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of redemption ſhall litle profite vs, if wee goe forwarde in the way of wickedneſſe and vngodlineſſe.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> The very ſame compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon almoſt is in <hi>Paule, 1. Corinth. 10.</hi> verſ. <hi>6.</hi> Thoſe whom God indued with greate bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, whom hee exalted to the ſame degree of honor (as hee at this day hath vouchedſafe to ſhew vppon vs) afterwarde hee puniſhed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueerly for their rebellion and diſobedience. In vayne is it therefore to bragge and to bee proude of the grace of God, if our deedes are not anſwerable to our vocation and callinge. <hi>I.</hi> And litle ſhall it profit,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mlerus.</note> that wee haue once by baptiſme layde away our ſinnes, vnleſſe with conſtant mindes wee dayly goe forwarde from better to better, from vertue to vertue, to the obtayning of the celeſtiall and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lyfe.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> This name <hi>(people)</hi> is very hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably taken for the holy and elect nation: as if hee ſhould ſay, it profited them nothing that by this ſingular pryuiledge they were recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the couenante, when afterward they fell away by diſobedience. It followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee deſtroyed them which afterward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26942:17"/>
not]</hi> Heere he noteth the welſpring of all euill. For hence is it that <hi>Moſes</hi> doth recken vp all their ſinnes, becauſe they would not ſuffer themſelues to bee ruled by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God. For faith conſiſteth in obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes God all our lyfe longe.<note place="margin">Aug. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> It is not without cauſe therefore that Chriſte ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes: <hi>Except yee beleeue that I am hee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ihon. 8. verſ. 24.</note> 
               <hi>yee ſhall dye in your ſinnes.</hi> And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> author of the epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Hebr.</hi> Cha. <hi>4.</hi> verſ. <hi>2. For vnto vs was the gospell preached, as well as vnto them: but the worde which they heard did not profite them, not being coupled wyth faith to them that heard. M.</hi> Let them therefore take heede that are called by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of (Chriſtians and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding vnder this colour and title doe turne the grace of God into wantonnes) leaſt that happen vnto them, as did to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. Luth.</note> And in very deede, from the time that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery firſt began, and that the goſpell in our age lay hidden, one plague hath followed ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by which God hath taken vengeance on the vnbeleeuers, and hath made them a Pray to Satan.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The texte.</note> 
               <hi>The Angels alſo which kept not their firſt eſtate, but left their owne habitation, he hath reſerued in euerlaſting chaynes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:26942:18"/>
darckneſſe vnto the iudgement of the great day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Angels alſo which kept not their fyrſt eſtate] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> This ſeconde example th'Apoſtle <hi>S. Peter</hi> hath touched alſo in his <hi>2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ullinger</note> epiſtle, and <hi>2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aluin.</note> Chap. verſ. <hi>4. C.</hi> And it is an argumente taken from the more to the leſſe. For the ſtate and condition of Angels, is farre more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then ours, and yet notwithſtanding God reuenged their fallinge away from him with an horrible example. Therefore hee will not ſpare our vnfaythfulnes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ullinger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ane.</note> if we fal from grace, into the which hee hath called vs. <hi>B. L.</hi> When the Angels, ſayth hee, chaunged their moſte bleſſed and happy nature, into wickednes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther continued in their firſt eſtate, they were throwen out of heauen into hell, where they are kept in chaynes euen vntill that laſt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the which they ſhall receaue the ſentence of eternall damnation.<note place="margin">Aug. Mar.</note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ſpared not them, beinge ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent creatures, <hi>B</hi> if wee contynew not in our eſtate and callinge, doinge thoſe things, which become the chyldren of God, how ſhall wee eſcape his punyſhment?<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> This pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment verely hath bene layde vppon the inhabitants and indwellers of heauen, and ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26942:18"/>
excellent miniſters of God, ought dayly to be ſett before our eyes, leaſte at any tyme wee proudely contemne the grace of God, from whence wee fall headlonge into vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.<note place="margin">Aug. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> For the Lord doth no leſſe hate pryde nowe, and the contempt of his grace, then hee did in time paſt. Hee is no chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge, hee remayneth one and the ſelfe ſame God ſtill.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in this place may bee aptly taken as well for the beginninge, as for principallity. For <hi>Iudas</hi> ſignifieth, that therefore they ſuffered puniſhment, becauſe, deſpiſinge the goodnes of God they fell from their firſt callinge. And by and by hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth the ſame when hee ſayth: <hi>But lefte their owne habitation]</hi> For they left and forſoke theyr ſtanding wherein they were placed, as fugitiue &amp; daſtardly ſouldiars are wont to do in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of warres. It followeth. <hi>Hee hath reſerued in euerlaſtinge chaines vnder darkeneſſe vnto the iudgemente of the greate day]</hi> The cruelty of this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmente which the Apoſtle heere expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth is to bee noted. They were not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly free ſpirites, but they were alſo celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all powers, and nowe they are kepte in perpetuall Chaynes. They dydde not onelye enioye and beeholde the gloryous
<pb facs="tcp:26942:19"/>
lighte of God, but his brightneſſe alſo did ſhine in them in ſuch ſorte, as it might ſpread abroade it ſelfe into all the partes and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the world, like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne beames: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as nowe they are drowned in darkeneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. Mar.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is all one with the ſame that <hi>S. Peter</hi> wryteth of their punyſhment, althoughe in other wordes.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> Furthermore, wee muſt not fayne of our owne heades a place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the diuells are ſhut vp and holden bounde. For the Apoſtles woulde teach vs playnely, how miſerable their ſtate and condition is, ſithens the time they were depriued of their dignity for their Apoſtaſie or fallinge away from God. Whether ſo euer they goe, they drawe their chaynes after them, and remaine ouerwhelmed in their darckeneſſe. In the meane time their puniſhment is deferred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that great and extreme day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>A.</hi> But what wee muſt thinke and iudge of the fall of Angells,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng. Mar.</note> and howe ſoberly wee muſt reaſon and diſpute of ſuch matters, it hath bene ſufficiently ſpoken of in the ſecond epiſtle of <hi>S. Peter</hi> the ſeconde Chapter, the fourth verſe.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">The texte.</note>
               <hi>7. <hi>Euen as Sodome and Gomorrhe, and the cyties aboute them, which in like maner
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26942:19"/>
defiled themſelues with fornication, and followed ſtraunge fleſh, are ſet forth for an enſample, and ſuffer the payne of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall fire.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euen as Sodome and Gomorrhe, and the cyties aboute them] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> The third example is taken out of the booke of <hi>Geneſis</hi> the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chap. verſe twenty-fourth,<note place="margin">Bulling</note> 
               <note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C</hi> and it is more generall: for it ſheweth, that God will puniſhe all the wicked, one with another, no kinde of men excepted.<note place="margin">Aug. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> Hee leaueth out the example of that olde worlde, that pery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ouerflowed with water, whereof <hi>Peter</hi> maketh mention. But this deſtruction of the Sodomites is no leſſe horrible, wherein the Lord would ſhewe moſt clearely, how much the vncleanneſſe and filthyneſſe of mans life doth diſpleaſe him, and the forgetfulneſſe of his heauenly benefits.<note place="margin">L. Pely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane.</note> 
               <hi>L.</hi> Sodome (ſayth he) and Gomorrha, and the cyties adioyninge thereabout, when they floryſhed with all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance and plenty of thinges, (euen <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> witneſſinge the ſame in the thirteenth of <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 13. verſ. 10.</note> verſe the tenth) becauſe they abuſed the louing kindneſſe and goodneſſe of God in royetouſneſſe &amp; pleaſure, defiling them ſelues with all kinde of wicked and abhominable fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:26942:20"/>
ſodainely the wrath of God deſtroyed them, to bee an example doubtleſſe to others, which abuſe the benefits of Chriſte through vncleannes and filthines of lyfe. <hi>Which in like maner defiled them ſelues with fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> When hee ſaith here that the cyties thereaboute co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted fornication in like ſorte with them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aluin.</note> this ought to be referred not to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and to the Angels, but to Sodome and Gomorrhe; this pronowne <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> being the maſculine gender notwithſtanding. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle <hi>Iudas</hi> reſpected rather y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabitours thereof, then the place. <hi>And followed ſtrang fleſhe</hi>) Hee ſayth to goe after ſtrange fleſh, for to be vyolently drawen to monſtrous and vnlawfull luſtes contrary to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon courſe and kinde of nature. For we know that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domytes were not content with common and vnlawfull lyberty of harlots, but were polu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and defiled with a more execrable and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary faſhion of filthines. It followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Are ſet forth for an enſample, and ſuffer the paine of eternall fyre]</hi> Hee affyrmeth that the fyre, wherewith the fiue cyties periſhed and were conſumed, is a type and figure of the eternall and euerlaſtinge fyre. Therefore God at that time appoynted it to bee a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table document and inſtruction to keepe men
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26942:20"/>
in his awe and feare, euen till the ende of the worlde. Hence is it that mention is ſo often made thereof inſcripture. For when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of God doe minde to ſet forth ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and fearefull example of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in writinge, paintinge it out as it were vnder the figure of fire and brimſtone, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude to the deſtruction &amp; ouerthrowe of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Gomorrhe. <hi>A.</hi> As <hi>Eſay. 13</hi> verſ. <hi>19.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hieremy 49.</hi> verſ. <hi>18.</hi> and <hi>50.</hi> verſ. <hi>40. Amos 4.</hi> verſ. <hi>11. Soph. 2.</hi> verſ. <hi>9.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluin.</note> Wherefore it is not without cauſe that <hi>Iudas</hi> ſtriketh a terror and feare into the heartes and mindes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all times and ages, when hee layeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them ſuch a glaſſe as this is to dare and looke vppon. By this alſo, that the Apoſtle betaketh the wicked and vngodly to eternall fyre, wee gather, that that fearefull ſpectacle and fighte that <hi>Moſes</hi> deſcribeth in the <hi>19.</hi> of <hi>Geneſis:</hi> was but onely a type and figure of greater puniſhment to come. Of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fyre reade more in the twenty-fiue of <hi>Matth.</hi> verſe the forty-one.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The texte.</note> 
               <hi>Lykewiſe theſe being deceaued by drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, defile the fleſhe, deſpiſe rulers, and ſpeake euyll of them that are in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26942:21"/>
               <hi>Likewiſe theſe being deceiued by dreames] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Here the Apoſtle deſcribeth &amp; ſetteth forth theſe deceauers to this ende,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ullinger.</note> not to eaſe him ſelfe of choller, but that they being knowne, the godly may the better ſhunne and avoyde them. This doth ſo agree with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinges that haue bene ſpoken of before, that looke what the Sodomites and Gamorrheans did, who were deſtroyed and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed by fyre ſent from heauen, the ſame alſo doe theſe deceauers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Caluin.</note>
               <hi>C.</hi> Notwithſtandinge hee doth not ſo preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vrge this ſimilitude, as if he compared the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all points to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sodomits, of whom he here maketh mencion, or to the fallinge angells, or to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnfaithfull or incredulous people. Only hee declareth that they are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veſſells of wrath appoynted to deſtruction: neyther can they eſcape the handes of God, but that one time or other hee will puniſhe them in like ſorte, that other may take example thereby. For y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> purpoſe and intente of the Apoſtell is, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite or forbid the godly to whom hee wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth, that they keepe no company with theſe deceauers.<note place="margin">Bullinger</note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> Firſt hee calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dreamers yea, rather mocked and deceaued by dreames, (that is) ſeduced &amp; blinded, which through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vanity of their mindes, imbrace falſe thinges for true thinges, to weete, pleaſures, &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26942:21"/>
luſtes, which make men wretched and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, rather then bleſſed &amp; happy. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they dreame, they thinke them ſelues to bee in great ioy &amp; felicity, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are far deceiued.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>They defile the fleſhe] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Hee ſaith, that they defiled their fleſh, as it were dreaminge: by the which words, he noteth their blockiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and impudency. As if hee ſhould ſay, they did as it were proſtrate and throw downe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to all kinde of filthines and vncleannes, in ſuch ſorte, that euen the moſt wicked would abhorre ſo to doe; whereby theſe dreamers doe ſhew, how ſhameles &amp; ſenceles they were. This is a metaphoricall kinde of ſpeakinge, whereby hee ſignifieth, that they were ſo dull and altogether blockiſhe, that without all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of honeſty, they gaue them ſelues to all vncleannes. But here the antitheſis or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon is to be noted, when he ſaith, that they defiled the fleſhe: that is to ſay: that as they miſuſed theyr vnhoneſt partes, ſo they contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and deſpiſed, as a thing reprochfull and of none accoumpt, that which hath the chiefe ſoueraignty in the gouerning and rulinge of mankinde: &amp; therefore he addeth immediatly. <hi>They deſpiſe rulers] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> They doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defile themſelues with all kinde of vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">Bullinger</note> but deſpiſe alſo their rulers and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
<pb facs="tcp:26942:22"/>
and ſuch as bee placed in high authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and office, confirmed and ſtabliſhed by a lawe, and appointed by God himſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace tranquillity &amp; honeſty might be preſerued and maintained amonge men.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> By this place it appeareth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe men were mouers of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and tumult, they ſought to liue without rule or gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that being deliuered from the bondage and feare of the lawe, they might ſinne the more freely. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in theſe lawleſſe men, two thinges doe alwayes concurre and meete together: the one, free liberty to ſinne and to liue as they luſt: the other, dyſalowing of magiſtrates, and the ſubuerſion of all good and ciuile order. Now as they ſought by all meanes to liue at liberty, to bee ſubiecte to no lawe, ſo it is euident by the wordes of the Apoſtle, that they vſed to clatter &amp; to ſpeake very ſaucely &amp; contunicliouſly of magiſtrates, and of ſuch as were in office and authority. And therefore it followeth. <hi>And ſpeake euill of them</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that are in authority]</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as franticke men at this day do fume and frett when they are kept vnder the rule &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of magiſtrates, &amp; exclame and cry out like madde men, againſt all ciuill pollicy and good gouernment, and that the ſworde of iuſtice, is but a prophane thinge, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26942:22"/>
to the doctrine of piety: to conclude, they would haue neither kinges, princes, nor magiſtrates to bee of the church of God,<note place="margin">M. Luth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> but vtterly banniſhe and expell them. <hi>M.</hi> But we teach thus: that as longe as we lyue here one this earth, we muſt bee ſubiect and obay the magiſtrate. For the faith of Chriſte doth not diſalowe outwarde pollicie, and cyuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. And therefore it is not lawfull for any man to withdrawe him ſelfe from obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence due to the magiſtrate, as our Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes and popiſhe Byſſhops doe: for there be many decrees extant of our hygh Byſſhops, bearing this title; <hi>Of eccleſiasticall liberty or freedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>A</hi> which muſt needes bee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meere inuentions of Satan, if this doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doe come from the holy ghoſte, as it is not of vs to bee doubted.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9. <hi>Yet Mychaell th'archangell, when hee ſtroue againſt the diuell,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The texte.</note> 
               <hi>and dyſputed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the body of Moſes, durſt not giue raylinge ſentence, but ſayde, the Lorde rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet Mychaell th'archangell] <hi>M.</hi>
               </hi> This is one of the places, for the which,<note place="margin">M. Luth.</note> the olde auncient writers in time paſt, haue reiected
<pb facs="tcp:26942:23"/>
this epiſtle, becauſe hee bringeth in here an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample which is red in no place of ſcripture, to weete, that <hi>(Mychaell th'archangell did ſtriue with the diuell aboute the body of Moſes.)</hi> Some do thinke, that herehence this contention grewe, for becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many notable thinges are written of <hi>Moſes,</hi> how God buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, neither doth any man know yet where his ſepulchre is. Then, that the ſcripture doth witneſſe of him, that there aroſe no prophet in <hi>Iſraëll</hi> like vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom the Lorde knewe face to face. <hi>Deut. 34.</hi> verſ. <hi>10.</hi> Syth <hi>Moſes</hi> therefore was of ſo worthy eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the doctors doe affyrme that an Angel ſent from heauen did bury him, neither doth any man knowe of his ſepulchre to this day. And it was done for this cauſe, leaſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> if they had had the body of <hi>Moſes</hi> being ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſo famous a prophet, ſhould vpon this occaſion haue fallen to Idolatry: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence afterward grew this contention &amp; ſtrife aboute the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> whereof <hi>Iudas</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention here, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuell would haue it knowne where the body of <hi>Moſes</hi> was, to geue the people occaſion to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit Idolatry to the ſame.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> Furthermore, becauſe they thinke this hiſtory to bee taken out of ſome Apocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall booke, hence came it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this epiſtle was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26942:23"/>
ſo litle eſteemed. But whereas the <hi>Iewes</hi> haue ſo many things by tradition of the fathers, it is no abſurdity to ſay, that <hi>Iudas</hi> declareth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which hath bene receaued from hand to hande many yeares and longe agoe. Wee know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely that many fooliſhe toyes and trifles haue bene receaued vnder this title and name of <hi>(Tradition):</hi> as the papiſts at this day doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken euery fooliſhe and vnſauery fable of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Monckes into this cataloge or kalender. But this doth not binder, but that they had certaine vnwritten hiſtories. That the Lord buried <hi>Moſes,</hi> it is out of all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie, that is, that his ſepulchre was not knowen, it was the ſecret purpoſe and will of God, the cauſe whereof, wee haue already touched. What maruaile then is it, if Satan goe about ſo bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily to bring to lighte the body of the prophet being hid by the ſecret counſaile of God. But the Angels withſtoode him, as they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ready at hand to miniſter to the Lord. <hi>Pſal. 103.</hi> verſ. <hi>20.21.</hi> And truly wee doe ſee, that Satan in all times and ages hath not ceaſed to laboure very earneſtly in this point, and to ſeeke all meanes, and to ſpeake prouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bially, to tourne euery ſtone, that is, to leaue no way vnattempted, to geue fooliſhe and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men an occaſion to commit Idolatry
<pb facs="tcp:26942:24"/>
to ſo many bodies, as there bee ſeruantes and ſaintes of God. Wherefore this epiſtle ought not to be doubted of, by reaſon of this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, becauſe it is in ſcripture no where to bee founde. It followeth. <hi>Durſt not giue rayling ſentence]</hi> That <hi>Mychaell</hi> is brought in alone diſputinge againſt Satan, it is no newe thinge. Wee knowe that there are thowſandes of Aungells alwayes ready at hande, to doe the will and commaundement of God. <hi>Daniell 7.</hi> verſ. <hi>10.</hi> For hee maketh his choiſe of this or that Aungel, and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him to doe this or that, as pleaſeth him.</p>
            <p>It followeth. <hi>But ſayde the Lorde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke thee]</hi> This alſo is in <hi>Zachary.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zacha. 3. verſ. 2.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord reproue thee then Satan,</hi> or brydle thee, or keepe thee vnder. It is a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the greater to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſe, as they call it. <hi>M.</hi> As if <hi>Iudas</hi> ſhould ſay,<note place="margin">M. Luth.</note> although <hi>Mycha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> were an Archangell, yet durſt he not curſſe and rayle againſt the diuell: and yet theſe blaſpheminge ſeducers are not afrayde, nor aſhamed, to treade vnder their feete, as it were, the powers that are ordeyned of God, and to curſſe and ſpeake euill of them that are in authority, euen to the eyght &amp; ninth degree, beinge nothinge elſe but weake and frayle men. And this Archaungell feared to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26942:24"/>
vtter any raylinge worde agaynſt the wicked diuell, reprobate and already damned, but ſayd onely, <hi>The Lord reproue thee and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> This argument <hi>Peter</hi> hath handled more briefly in his ſecond epiſtle verſ. eleuenth.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10. <hi>But theſe ſpeake euill of thoſe thynges which they know not, and what thinges they knowe naturally, as beaſtes whych are without reaſon, in theſe things they corrupte them ſelues.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But theſe ſpeake euill of thoſe things which they know not] <hi>I.</hi>
               </hi> Hee hath a reſpect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that ſayinge:<note place="margin">Imlerus.</note> 
               <hi>A foole aunſwereth before hee vnderſtandeth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouerb. 1 verſ. 28. &amp; 18. verſ. 13.</note> 
               <hi>a very foole when hee holdeth his tongue is counted wyſe: and hee that ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his lyppes is eſteemed prudent.</hi> Theſe in like ſorte are worthely to bee counted fooles, which goe about to defend their ignorance by euill reproches.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C. Iudas</hi> therefore ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that they are very beaſtly, blockiſhe and dulheaded, not knowinge nor vnderſtandinge what is worthy of honour, neyther what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth or appertayneth thereunto: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge, they are thus farre made bolde, that they are not aſhamed to condemne thoſe thinges that paſſe their reache.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26942:25"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug. Mar.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> This wee may clearely and euidently ſee &amp; behold in the Pope him ſelfe, and his cornuted or horned Byſſhops,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar. Lut.</note> 
               <hi>M</hi> which knew nothing els, but to excommunicate, curſſe, and to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to Satan, not onely kinges and Princes of the worlde, but God alſo him ſelfe and his bleſſed ſaintes, which thing is to bee ſeene in the Bull of the ſupper of the Lorde. They knowe, or at leaſt they ſhould know, that our ſaluation conſiſteth of fayth and charity: they cannot away to heare their workes ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and to be comdemned: they cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde to heare vs talke and reaſon one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that wee are ſaued onely by Chryſtes workes and merites: and therefore doe they blaſpheme and ſpeake euill of all chryſtian doctrine,<note place="margin">Aug. Mar.</note> whereof they are ignorante. <hi>A.</hi> The knowledge of tongues alſo they deſpiſe, which they haue not attained vnto, but in their owne dotinges, and fayned fanſies, they doe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly pleaſe them ſelues, alwayes erring and leadinge others into error. <hi>2. Tymo. 3.</hi> verſ. <hi>13.</hi> It followeth. <hi>And what things they knowe naturally, as beaſtes which are without reaſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>in theſe thinges they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt them ſelues.] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Heere hee affirmeth that they were infected with diuers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry kindes of vyces, becauſe beaſtlyke they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26942:25"/>
were mooued and ſtirred vnto thoſe thinges, which are ſubiect to our corporall ſences, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping neither modeſty nor meaſure, but alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether weltring and wallowing them ſelues like hogges and ſwyne in their filthines and vncleannes. This aduerbe <hi>(naturally)</hi> is a worde that is oppoſite or contrary to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and iudgement. For the rage and vyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of nature, doth raygne and beare rule in brute beaſtes onely. But in men, reaſon muſt haue the chiefe gouernance, to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and to bridle their appetites and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. <hi>A.</hi> To bee briefe,<note place="margin">Aug. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iudas</hi> pronowceth ſuch ſeducers as theſe bee, ſenceleſſe, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all reaſon: which <hi>S. Peter</hi> alſo confirmeth, in theſe wordes. <hi>But theſe as brute beaſtes, led with ſenſuality, and made to bee taken and deſtroyed, ſpeake euill of the thinges that they vnderſtand not, and ſhall periſhe through their owne corruption, and receaue the rewarde of vnryghteouſneſſe. 2. Pet. 2.</hi> verſ. <hi>12.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11. <hi>Woe bee vnto them, for they are gonne in the way of Caine, and are vtterly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the error of Balaam for lucres ſake, and haue peariſhed in the gaine ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of Core.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Woe bee vnto them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bullinge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>for] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Heer the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb facs="tcp:26942:26"/>
deſcribeth and ſetteth forth againe theſe men, theſe crafty deceauers, by other haynous and miſchieuous actes &amp; deedes that they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: to weete, they murdered their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, they ſlew their owne kinſmen &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, they were couetous, ambitious, trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luin.</note> mouers of ſedition. <hi>C.</hi> Yet all this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge, it may be wondred at why the Apoſtle doth ſo ſharply reprehend them.</p>
            <p>Whereas hee ſayd before, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Mychaell</hi> the Archaungell was not ſuffered ſo much as to ſhew any token of contumely or raylinge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Satan. His minde was not to ſet down this to be followed as a generall rule, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew, and that briefly, by the example of <hi>Machaell,</hi> how intollerable this madneſſe of theirs was, when they did ſo prowdly, and ſo malapertly rayle againſt that, which God would haue reuerenced and honored. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, <hi>Mychaell</hi> myght lawfully haue lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and thundred out as it were curſſes and banninges againſt Satan, as wee ſee many times how earneſtly and vehemently the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets doe manace and threaten the wicked. But foraſmuch, as <hi>Mychaell</hi> abſtayned from ſuch ſeuere dealinge, which otherwiſe hee mought lawfully haue vſed, what madneſſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26942:26"/>
is this of theirs, to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boundes and lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes of meaſure, to be ſhewed towards the creatures of God which excell in glory?</p>
            <p>Moreouer, when hee doth ſo expreſly touche theſe ſeducers, hee doth ſo much wyſhe them to bee puniſhed, as to forewarne them what ſhall bee the ende of them, and that for this cauſe, and to this ende, leaſt they ſhould draw others to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame deſtruction with them before they bee ware: ſo that <hi>Iudas</hi> coulde not more liuelyer deſcribe them and reproue them, then by vſinge theſe examples, and therefore ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that puniſhments remayne for them.</p>
            <p>It followeth. <hi>For they haue gone in the way of Caine]. <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> He ſayth,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> that they were the followers of <hi>Caine,</hi> who being vnthankful to God, peruerting and corrupting his true worſhip and ſeruice,<note place="margin">M. Luth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> berefte him ſelfe of his byrthrighte, <hi>M</hi> and ſlewe his brother <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> for this onely cauſe, becauſe <hi>Abell</hi> was more ryghteouſe and godly then hee: for God accepted <hi>Abells</hi> ſacrifice, and not <hi>Caines: Gen. 4.</hi> verſ. <hi>5.</hi> and <hi>1. Ihon. 3.</hi> verſ. <hi>12.</hi> The way therefore of <hi>Caine,</hi> is to leane and to ſticke to their owne workes, &amp; to blaſpheme &amp; ſpeake euill of workes, which are good workes in deede: and at a word, to ſley and kill them that goe the ryght way. In this poynte the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes
<pb facs="tcp:26942:27"/>
ſhewe them ſelues very ſtout and bolde, <hi>B</hi> for they follow the manners and condicions of thieues and robbers,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llinger</note> perſecuting through couetouſnes and enuy, the true followers and profeſſors of pure and ſincere religion. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. <hi>And are vtterly geuen to the error of Balaam for lucres ſake] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Hee ſayth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luin.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> like vnto <hi>Balaam</hi> they were deceaued by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, becauſe they corrupted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true doctrine of piety &amp; godlines for filthy lucres ſake. But the Metaphor that hee vſeth, doth expreſſe &amp; ſet forth ſomewhat more at large their filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and impiety: for hee ſayth, that lyke as a riuer flowing ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bankes, ſo were they gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to all kinde of ryotouſneſſe, and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe paſſinge meaſure.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug. Mar. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Luth.</note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> This in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes euen blinde men may ſee. <hi>M.</hi> They thought it beſt to keepe them ſelues in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſecret for a time, truſtinge vppon Gods heauenly grace: and nowe I wis they come forth in great companies, ſeperating them ſelues into diuerſe &amp; ſundry kindes of workes, and doe heere and there diſperſe them ſelues abroade. All that they doe is for lucres ſake, and for couetouſneſſe of money, to fill their panches, and to ſerue diuerſe luſtes. Of this the reader may ſee more, in the ſecond epiſtle of <hi>Peter</hi> the ſecond Chap. the fifteenth verſe.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26942:27"/>
It followeth. <hi>And haue peryſhed in the gayne ſaying of Core] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Thirdly,<note place="margin">Caluin</note> he ſaith that they followed the gaine ſaying of <hi>Core,</hi> to weete, becauſe they troubled the peaceable and quiet ſtate of the church.<note place="margin">Bulling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>B. Core</hi> beinge ouercomne of ambition, would violently take vpon him the prieſthoode, and therefore made a greate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motion and ſturre in the tents of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> But hee did not longe preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Moſes.</hi> For by and by the earth ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſwallowed vp him with all his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, ſo that they went downe to hell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyue: ſhewing to all mortall men by this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible example, that are led and ſeduced by the ſpirite of pride and arrogancy, that ſtirre vp the multitude againſt the true miniſters, what they muſt looke for.</p>
            <p>To this example the Apoſtle compareth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeducers of his time, nay rather of all tymes and ages, which take vpon them the office and Function of teachinge, reiectinge and litle eſteeming in very deede the true and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere teachers of truth and verity. Hence is it that theſe lewde ſpeeches proceede from our owne countrymen, papiſtes, to weete, theſe wordes:<note place="margin">☜</note> Who hath opened or reuealed to theſe vyle varlets and lewde knaues (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the true miniſters of Gods worde) the
<pb facs="tcp:26942:28"/>
vnderſtanding and meaninge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures? As for vs Catholiks, our holy father y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, hath made &amp; ordayned vs prieſtes, wee are the illuminate doctors taught from God himſelf, wee onely are called maiſters, to vs onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth the office and function of teachinge, &amp; to giue determinate ſentence and iudgemente of all matters and caſes.</p>
            <p>By theſe wordes they ſtirre vp the mindes both of certaine princes, and of the inferior ſorte, againſt good men, defenders and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes bearers to the truth, whom they vexe, &amp; perſecute, but to their owne deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Luth.</note>
               <hi>M.</hi> They impute vnto vs that we are mouers of ſedition, when wee exclaime and inueighe againſt their moſt wicked and corrupt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and their peruerſe doctrine, when as it is they themſelues that rayſe vp tumultes. Chriſte is our <hi>Aaron</hi> and high prieſt, whom alone wee all ought to heare, and to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him to bee the Byſſhop and high prieſt of holy thinges: but the Pope, his Byſhops and Cardinalles will none of that. For they doe wonderfully extoll and magnifie them ſelues: they challenge to them ſelues all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, rule, and power: and as for Chriſte, and the honor due vnto him, they make ſmale ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compte thereof: they ſpoyle him of all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26942:28"/>
               <hi>B.</hi> But they ſhall vnderſtand and feele one day with whom they haue kept all this bitter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention; when, with the Corytes,<note place="margin">Bullin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> they ſhall receaue condigne puniſhment:<note place="margin">M. Lut.</note> 
               <hi>M</hi> nay but God hath euen now already punyſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the earth hath ſwallowed them vp and ouerwhelmed them: that is, they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther earthly, and as it were drowned nad bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in ſenſuality, and all kinde of volupteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and pleaſure, that are nothinge els but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the very worlde it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The text<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theſe are ſpottes in your feaſtes of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, when they feaſte with you, without all feare feedinge them ſelues: cloudes they are without water, carried about of wyndes, trees withered at fruite gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and without fruite, twiſe deade, &amp; plucked vp by the rootes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are ſpottes in your feaſtes] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to by examples he hath depainted forth in liuely colours theſe deceauers and ſeducers.<note place="margin">Bullinger</note> Now the very ſame deceauers he ſetteth forth againe by moſte euident and liuely coloures of ſimilitudes. But before hee bringeth forth theſe parables or ſimilitudes, hee warneth vs aforehande, that ſuch deceauers are ſpottes
<pb facs="tcp:26942:29"/>
in your feaſt of Charity.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> For this greeke worde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifieth a banquet or feaſt, which the faithfull are wonte to keepe among them ſelues, for no other cauſe, but to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and declare thereby, the vnity and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ought to bee among brethren. But theſe wicked and vngodly ſeducers (ſaith he) defiled and polluted theſe feaſtes, with their vngodly and vnciuile behauiour, feedinge them ſelues afterwarde with banquet after banquet moſt diſſolutely and beyonde all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. In the feaſts of the godly, there was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and honeſt behauiour, frugality and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance. And therefore they thought it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely and vnlawfull to admit into their company any wicked and vngodly perſons, who make a God of their belly. Touchinge the brotherly meetings of the godly at their feaſtes, <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his <hi>Apologitico</hi> the <hi>30.</hi> Chapter doth very trimly deſcribe and ſet forth. See <hi>Peter</hi> alſo in his ſecond epiſtle the ſecond Chapter, verſe thirteenth.</p>
            <p>It followeth. <hi>When they feaſte with you without all feare, feeding them ſelues] <hi>L.</hi>
               </hi> That is to ſay,<note place="margin">L. Pely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane. Caluin.</note> when you faſt, they feaſte, geuing them ſelues to royetouſnes, and glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony. <hi>C.</hi> Some bookes haue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, feaſting together with you. If
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26942:29"/>
you like it better to reade it ſo, then the ſence is, that they are not onely ſhameleſſe, but alſo burdenous and troubleſome, as they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would ſtuffe and fill their panches, vpon the common coſt and charges of the Church. But <hi>Peter</hi> wryteth ſomewhat otherwiſe, <hi>That they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in their deceauings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. verſ. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and eate with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the faythfull.</hi> As if hee ſhoulde ſay, yee bee not well aduiſed to feede and to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe ſuch hurtfull beaſtes and venemous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentes, yea twice foolyſhe to fulfill their ryo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe and waſtfull ſpending. And I would to God there were at this day more diſcretion and aduiſed iudgement in the good and godly men, who while they ſhew them ſelues fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and ouer gentle to the wicked, bring great hurte and damage to the whole church. <hi>B.</hi> This alſo might well bee applyed to idle monkes and ſuch like.<note place="margin">Bullinge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> For the only and chiefeſt care that they had, was to feede &amp; to pamper vp themſelues: they are nothing els but ſpots, corruption, infamy, and a burden to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, whereof they ought to bee the greateſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, lightes, and pyllers. It followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Without all feare feeding themſelues] <hi>A.</hi>
               </hi> That is to ſay, careleſly, impudently,<note place="margin">A. Marl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reuerence eyther of God or of his church. <hi>Cloudes they are wythout water]
<pb facs="tcp:26942:30"/>
                  <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> The two ſimilitudes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in <hi>Peter</hi> hee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth into one,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uin.</note> and yet of one and the ſelfe ſame ſence and meaninge. For both of them doe often times touch their vayne oſtentation and bragging. For when theſe varlets make a ſhew of many fayre promiſes outwardly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly they become barren and fruitleſſe. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as the cloudes toſt &amp; carried aboute with great windes and tempeſts, doe make a ſhew and hope of much rayne, ſodainely doe vaniſhe to nothinge, ſo theſe deceauers make great boaſt, but litle roſte, great promiſes outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but nothinge ſo inwardly. <hi>Peter</hi> addeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimilitude of <hi>Wells dry and without water.</hi> But <hi>Iudas</hi> gathereth together many Metaphors to one and the ſelfe ſame ende. It followeth. <hi>Trees wythered at fruite gatheringe, and without fruite] <hi>I.</hi>
               </hi> They are like alſo vnto trees that loſe their leaues at harueſt time,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mſerus.</note> that wyther a way, and bring forth no fruite. So theſe deceauers are naughty and deade trees, that muſt bee mored and plucked vp by the rootes, if they bringe forth no fruyte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Mar.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Some doe turne it, <hi>rotten trees:</hi> that is, which bringe forth no fruite, but ſuch as is corrupte and wythered.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lling.</note> 
               <hi>Twyce deade] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Beſides this they lyue a lyfe not aunſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the euangelycall doctrine, drawinge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26942:30"/>
alſo with them both with their wicked doctrine, and euill example to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>It followeth. <hi>And plucked vp by the rootes]</hi> That is, they are like vnto trees plucked vp by the rootes, beinge paſt all hope of ſprynginge and ſproutinge agayne, howſoeuer the leaues appeare outwardely, yet wythin they, haue neyther Sappe nor Iuyce.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13. <hi>They are the raging waues of the Sea,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out their owne ſhame, they are wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſtarres, to whom is reſerued the miſt of darknes for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They are the raging waues of the Sea] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Furthermore,<note place="margin">Bullin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> hee lykeneth them to the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Sea, lyfting and caſting vp their waues on hygh.<note place="margin">Caluin</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> Euen ſo theſe deceauers pufte vppe with pryde, doe nought elſe but blowe and pufe out their ſwellinge and prowde wordes of hautyneſſe and vanityes, ſauouring nothinge at all of the ſpirite, whereby they caſt men into a brutiſhe kynde of amazed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and aſtonyſhmente.<note place="margin">Bullin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> For as the water of the Sea the more that it is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and toſſed with ſharp ſtormes and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell tempeſtes of wynde and weather, the
<pb facs="tcp:26942:31"/>
more filth and froth it gathereth, and fometh: ſo theſe wicked ſeducers, the more outcries they make, and ſtirre vp ſeditious tumults, the more they make manifeſt to all men their ſhameleſſenes &amp; infamy.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> The like in theſe our dayes are theſe phantaſticall ſpirits that terme them ſelues <hi>Lybertines.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iuely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ily of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> A man would ſay that they doe nothinge els but thunder, For they ſcorne and diſdaine at the common and vſuall kinde of ſpeakinge, and haue deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and fayned to themſelues certaine ſtrange and proper kindes and formes of ſpeaches. And after they thinke that their ſchollers be rapte into the heauens, ſodainely they fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to beaſtly errours. For they fayne that to be the ſtate of innocency, where there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwene honeſt and vnhoneſt thinges. They fayne that to bee a ſpirituall life, when euery man (ſettinge all feare aparte) doth careleſſely and to to much giue him ſelfe to his owne appetite and ſenſuality. They ſay that wee are made Gods, becauſe God doth as it were ſucke and ſup vp our ſpirites, when they leaue the body. This their errour ought to make vs the more carefull with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to imbrace the ſimplicity of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, leaſt diſputing and reaſoning thereof more curiouſly and philoſophically then it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:26942:31"/>
behooueth vs, wee doe not ſo much as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche vnto heauen, but rather fall and bee drowned ſodainely in the <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe erroures.<note place="margin">Bulling</note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> But it ſeemeth that this Parable of <hi>Iudas</hi> was taken out of the prophet <hi>Eſayes</hi> fifty ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th Chap. verſe <hi>20.</hi> where it is thus wrytten: <hi>The wicked are like the raginge ſea that cannot reſt, whoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fometh with the myre and grauel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It followeth. <hi>They are wandring ſtarres] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> So theſe deceauers are called,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> becauſe they dazell the eyes with the ſimilitude or likeneſſe of lighte, that ſoone vaniſheth away and peariſheth. <hi>B.</hi> So theſe falſe teachers,<note place="margin">Bullinge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> doe ſeeme to them ſelues to bee brighte ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtarres, as who woulde ſay, illuminate Doctors, Lightes of the worlde, profounde clarkes. But becauſe they ſtand not to their opinion, nor follow the conſtant and knowne truth, but are ruled rather by their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they make ſhipwracke of the vnwiſe and ignorant. It followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whom the miſte of darckeneſſe is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for euer] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Now he threatneth them iudgement,<note place="margin">Bulling.</note> that the faythfull may take the better heede of them: as if hee ſhoulde ſay, althoughe they ſeeme nowe to raygne as Lordes and kynges, yet notwithſtandinge
<pb facs="tcp:26942:32"/>
they ſhall not eſcape the iudgement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. For hee reſerueth them to bee punyſhed with Satan in that helliſhe and eternall darkenes for euer.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erus.</note> 
               <hi>I.</hi> For it is meete and righte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they that deny Chryſte the true lighte in deede, bee delyuered to perpetuall darckneſſe for euer.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14. <hi>Enoch the ſeuenth from Adam propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before of ſuch,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The texte.</note> 
               <hi>ſaying, behold the Lord ſhall come with thowſands of ſaintes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">M. Luth.</note>
               <hi>Enoch the ſeuenth] <hi>M.</hi>
               </hi> This place is read no where in ſcripture: which is another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why ſome of the fathers haue not recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this epiſtle.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> But this propheſie ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth rather to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, vnwritten, or deliuered by tradition, then to be taken out of the bookes Apochriphall. For it may bee, that the auncient fathers commended this worthy ſayinge, to bee remembred of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. If any man demaunde, ſeeing that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like ſentences are to be found in ſcripture eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, why <hi>Iudas</hi> hath not cyted ſome writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten teſtymonies out of ſome one or other of the Prophets for confirmation thereof: The anſwere is eaſie. That <hi>Iudas</hi> would only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit pronounced of them in old time. And ſo doe the wordes here ſounde. For
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26942:32"/>
hee nameth <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeuenth from <hi>Adam,</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the antiquity of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> propheſie, to weete, becauſe it was extant in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt world.<note place="margin">M. Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>M.</hi> But herehence we do learne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world hath cauſed his worde to bee preached vnto ſome, (promiſing thereby grace and ſaluation to them that belieue, but to the vnfaithfull foreſhewinge iudgement and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation) euen till Chriſtes aſcention: from the which time the worde of the Lord hath bene preached openly to all the worlde. But before our Sauiour Chriſtes natiuity, God hath choſen only to himſelfe a certaine lineal deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Abraham:</hi> and from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Dauid:</hi> and ſo alonge from <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the mother of Chriſte, hee choſe ſome, to whom hee delyuered his worde. The worde of the Lorde therefore hath alwayes bene preached in the worlde, but neuer ſo openly as in theſe laſt dayes. After this manner alſo did our father <hi>Enoch</hi> preach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, which vndoubtedly hee had learned of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Adam,</hi> and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt. It followeth. <hi>Behold the Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> The preterper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect tence is put for he future tence propehti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally.<note place="margin">Caluin</note> 
               <hi>With thouſands of Angells]</hi> By theſe words he ſignifieth as well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells: for they ſhal both together garniſh &amp; ſo
<pb facs="tcp:26942:33"/>
forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tribunal ſeate of Chriſt, when he ſhal come to iudge the worlde. Hee ſaith thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes, euen as <hi>Daniell</hi> alſo telleth of many times ten thowſandes of Aungells, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Chap. verſe <hi>10.</hi> leaſt the multitude of the wicked, lyke the raging and vyolent ſea, ſhould burſt in vpon the children of God, and carry them away by force and violence, while they thinke it will come to paſſe, that the Lord in time will gather together thoſe that bee his, parte whereof are nowe inhabitinge the heauens, which wee cannot now ſee with our eyes, parte are here nowe in the worlde couered vnder the chaffe.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15. <hi>To giue iudgement againſt all men, and to rebuke all that are vngodly amonge them,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The texte</note> 
               <hi>of all their vngodly deedes which they haue vngodly committed, and of all their cruell ſpeakinges whych vngodly ſinners haue ſpoken againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">M. Luth.</note>
               <hi>To giue iudgement againſt all men] <hi>M.</hi>
               </hi> He ſpeaketh of the ſecond comminge of Chriſte, for at his firſt comminge, hee came not into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to iudge the world, but that the worlde by him might bee ſaued. <hi>Ihon</hi> the <hi>3.</hi> verſ. <hi>17. <hi>And to rebuke all that are vngodly amonge them]</hi> C.</hi> The vengeance of God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hangeth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26942:33"/>
ouer the heads of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reprobate, ought to keepe and conteine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> choſen &amp; elect of God in feare &amp; trembling. It followeth. <hi>Of all their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly deedes]</hi> Hee ſpeaketh of their deedes and wordes, becauſe theſe corruptors, did not only much harme and hurt by their wicked &amp; vngodly life, but alſo by their vncleane and peruerſe doctrine. It followeth. <hi>And of all their cruell ſpeakinges whych vngodly ſinners haue ſpoken againſt him] <hi>M.</hi>
               </hi> Theſe ſeducers ſpeake very boldly &amp; cruelly againſt the comminge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, they are impudent,<note place="margin">M. Luth</note> ſhameleſſe, and to too arrogant, they mocke and blaſpheame him. Hee calleth therefore their talking &amp; clattering <hi>(cruell ſpeakings)</hi> by reaſon of their obſtinate boldneſſe, their pride, and malepartneſſe.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16. <hi>Theſe are murmurers, complainers,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The texte</note> 
               <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after their own luſts, whoſe mouths ſpeake prowde things, they haue men in great reuerence becauſe of aduantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are murmurers] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Now againe he deſcribeth theſe ſeducers by their affections.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>L.</hi> Theſe (ſaith hee) becauſe they meaſure fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity in things pertayning outwardly to the body,<note place="margin">L. Pely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane.</note> if any trouble or affliction doe happen vnto them, by and by they are offended, they
<pb facs="tcp:26942:34"/>
waxe impacient, they murmur againſt God, they complaine of the ſhortnes of a mans life, that it is ſubiect to ſo many diſeaſes, miſeries and calamities, wiſhing that it were longer, &amp; not oppreſſed with ſo many euills: as who would ſay, being without hope of the life to come.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> And becauſe they delight themſelues in wicked luſts and deſires, they become wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and froward, hard to bee pleaſed, they are neuer at quiet. Herehence commeth their murmuring &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaining, they are neuer ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, let men doe what they can to pleaſe them.</p>
            <p>It followeth. <hi>And their mouth ſpeaketh proud things] <hi>I.</hi>
               </hi> That is,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lerus.</note> they come in with their high and lofty words, they ſet forth them ſelues very proudly and braggingly, they play the partes of <hi>Thraſoes</hi> out-right.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ullinger</note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> They tel vs wonderfull &amp; ſtrange oracles concerninge vertues lore, neuer heard of before, and all to deceaue vs: and yet they loue neyther truth nor vertue in dede &amp; from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart. It followeth. <hi>They haue men in great reuerence becauſe of aduantage] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Here he ſheweth that they are of a myſerable diſpoſition becauſe they would doe any ſeruile worke for lucres ſake.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly this inequality or greedines, by which they differ from other men, is to bee ſeene in ſuch Peſants as theſe be, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:26942:34"/>
when there is no man to check or controule them, their inſolencie and pryde is intollerable, they take much vpon them, they are very imperious. But ſuch as they feare, and ſtand in awe of, if they bee in hope of any thinge to be gotten by them, thoſe they doe ſhamefully flatter and ſmoth and ſoothe with ſweete and fayre words.<note place="margin">Bulling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> They ſpeake not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the truth &amp; matter it ſelfe, but ſuch thinges as are pleaſaunt vnto them, of whom they hope to reape ſome benefit or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity. They are therefore clawbacks &amp; moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les flatterers: becauſe they haue men in great reuerence &amp; admiration for adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage. Then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which kinde of men there are none more blind,<note place="margin">Caluin. A. Mar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> none more wicked. <hi>C. <hi>Perſon</hi>
               </hi> is here taken for any great man or noble man, <hi>A</hi> whereof <hi>S. Iames 2.</hi> verſ. <hi>1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>But yee beloued remember the woordes which were ſpoken before of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">
               <hi>18. <hi>How that they told you, that there ſhould be mockers in the laſt time, which ſhould walke after their owne vngodly luſtes.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But yee beloued reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber] <hi>I.</hi>
               </hi> Now he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thoſe to whom he writeth,<note place="margin">Imlerus. Bulling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>B</hi> to beware of theſe deceauers, &amp; of their great impiety &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlines,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C</hi> and therfore addeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> admonitions
<pb facs="tcp:26942:35"/>
and forewarninges both of the Prophets of olde time, and alſo of the Apoſtles, ſayinge: <hi>Remember the wordes which were ſpoken before of the Apoſtles] <hi>L.</hi>
               </hi> Let this bee an argument of no force,<note place="margin">Pely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne.</note> againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> author of this epiſtle, to proue him to be none of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles: ſith the old father ſpeaketh here of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles accordinge to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon manner, as they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue preached longe before him, ſo that it is not to be thought iniurious, that this author maketh mention of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Apoſtles of a ſinguler mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, whereby his meaning was, that men ſhould not ſo much credit and beleeue him, as other of the Apoſtles, ſpeaking and writinge the like, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelfe ſame things of falſe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and falſe Apoſtles.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lling.</note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> And therefore it is diligently to bee noted &amp; marked, that this worthy Apoſtle is not aſhamed to vſe, as his owne, yea and to alleage alſo the writinges &amp; ſayings of his fellowe Apoſtles. But in theſe our daies, a man may finde many proude &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant fellowes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> think great diſdaine to vſe other mens ſayinges bee they neuer ſo good &amp; godly: nay they think nothing well ſpoken or done, but that that cometh from them ſelues. It followeth. <hi>How that they tolde you] <hi>A. Iudas</hi>
               </hi> here ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Aug. Mar</note> not onely of the liuely preaching of the worde, but alſo of the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:26942:35"/>
of th'Apoſtles them ſelues. <hi>That there ſhould bee mockers in the laſt times] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> He vnderſtandeth that to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt time,<note place="margin">Caluin</note> wherein the ſtate and condition of the church being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued hath receaued a firme &amp; ſure promiſe of continuance euen to the ende of the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninge from the firſt comming of Chriſte: <hi>A</hi> of the which matter <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſpeaketh eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, but ſpecially in the <hi>1. Corin. 10.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> chap. verſ. <hi>11.</hi> And in the <hi>1.</hi> to <hi>Tymo.</hi> chap. <hi>4.</hi> verſ. <hi>1.</hi> and <hi>1.</hi> of <hi>Tymo.</hi> chap. <hi>3.</hi> verſ. <hi>1. <hi>There ſhall come mockers]</hi> C.</hi> He calleth them mockers after the vſuall maner of ſpeaking in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> which being drunken as it were with wicked prophaning &amp; contemning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of God, do breake forth into al kinde of beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behauiour, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no religion can keepe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> limites of their duty: the reaſon is; becauſe they feare not at all in their mindes the iudgement to come, they haue no hope in them of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed and euer during life. Euen as at this day, the world is full euery where of ſuch Epicures, contemners, &amp; deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of God, which ſhaking of altogether all reuerence and godly feare, doe very wickedly and maliciouſly, ſcorne and mocke at the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of piety, as though it were a tale or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that is tolde.<note place="margin">Bullinger</note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> Of this <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſpeaketh
<pb facs="tcp:26942:36"/>
very plentifully in his ſecond epiſtle the third Chap. verſe the third.</p>
            <p n="19">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he texte.</note>
               <hi>19. <hi>Theſe are makers of ſects, fleſhly, hauing not the ſpirite.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Caluin.</note>
               <hi>Theſe are makers] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Some greeke bookes hath the participle abſolutely: ſome doe adde the greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſence almoſt: for he vnderſtandeth ſuch as ſeuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church: they will haue no diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline exerciſed therein, they are altogether geuen to the fleſh and not to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite.<note place="margin">M. Luth.</note> 
               <hi>M.</hi> Hee alludeth to that ſaying of <hi>Peter:</hi> they bring in damnable ſects. For there bee ſom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudy and occupy their braines about nothinge els, but how they may cauſe diuiſion in the Church of God, to breake the vnity of the faith: as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon order taken amongſt Chriſtians, how euery man may pleaſe his neighbour, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ot, they cannot abyde it: but as touching their owne inuentions, &amp; deuiſes of their own making, which is nothing but hypocriſie, and falſe ſeruing of God, that pleaſeth them won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly well. It followeth. <hi>Fleſhly minded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>hauinge not the ſpirite] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Here <hi>minde,</hi> in this place, as it ſignifieth the life of man geuen to fleſhlineſſe, ſo it is oppoſite or contrary to the ſpirite: and therefore it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26942:36"/>
here, corruption of nature, ſuch as is in men not yet regenerated: for this degenerate nature of ours, which wee haue receaued and drawne as it were from our firſt parentes, is altogether corrupted, groſſe, and earthly, not able of it ſelfe to aſpire to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perfect knowledge of God, vnleſſe it bee renued and regenerated againe by his ſpirite, as wel teſtifieth <hi>S. Paule</hi> in his firſt epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> the ſecond chapter, the fouretenth verſe.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <hi>20. <hi>But yee dearely beloued,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The text</note> 
               <hi>edefie your ſelues in your moſt holy faith, praying in the holy-ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But yee dearely beloued] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Here againe hee exhorteth them as hee did before,<note place="margin">Bulling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in the truth, and to apply them ſelues to godlynes. <hi>C.</hi> He ſheweth them alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> meanes,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> how they may bee able to withſtand and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſleights &amp; ſubtilties of Satan, &amp; to make them of none effect: to wete, if they haue charity ioyned with faith, watching co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge of Chriſte. But as <hi>Iude</hi> is plentiful &amp; often in metaphors, ſo alſo he hath his proper kinde of ſpeaking, which is briefly of vs to be noted &amp; marked. It followeth. <hi>Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying your ſelues in your moſt holy fayth]</hi> He ſignifieth, that they muſt keepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grounde
<pb facs="tcp:26942:37"/>
and foundation of faith: and that it is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to be grounded &amp; ſtabliſhed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right fayth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. Mar.</note> vnleſſe wee grow &amp; increaſe dayly more and more therein. <hi>A.</hi> For to builde &amp; reare vp this foundation of faith is nothing elſe but to profit more and more, day by day, in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt: which cannot verely be done and brought to paſſe but by the operation and working of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt. <hi>C.</hi> Hee calleth their faith moſt holy faith,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aluin.</note> that they ſhoulde ſoundly and ſurely relie them ſelues thereuppon, and ſticke to the firmnes and ſtrongnes thereof,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> without waueringe. But for ſo much as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole perfection of man ſtandeth in faith, it ſeemeth a very abſurde thing that he biddeth to lay another foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as though faith were but the onely begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of mans perfection.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere </seg>
               </label> To this queſtion the Apoſtle aunſwereth: when he ſaith that men are builded vpon faith, immediatly he addeth charity, meaninge thereby a liuely faith, and not a deade faith. Except peraduenture ſome man had rather take it thus: that men are the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd to be builded vpon faith, ſo farre forth as they profit and increaſe therein, as we ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And verely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more that faith doth growe and increaſe, the more it ariſeth to a perfect building. After this ſorte here doth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26942:37"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde vs, to growe &amp; increaſe in faith to continue in prayer, to walke accordinge to charity. <hi>L.</hi> As if hee ſhoulde ſay:<note place="margin">L. Pely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cane.</note> you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are ſpirituall, giue diligence, that more and more, as liuely ſtones yee may bee ioyned together into the buildinge of God, cleauing faſt to the ſure foundation of your moſt holy faith. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>Praying in the holy-ghoſt] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> This is the reaſon of perſeuering, if we bee indued with the powre of the holy-ghoſt. As ofte therefore as mention is made of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant faith, wee muſt haue recourſe to prayer. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee are wonte to pray commonly for a faſhion ſake, hee addeth <hi>in ſpyrite.</hi> As if hee ſhoulde ſay: ſuch is the great dulneſſe and ſlougthfulneſſe of our frayle fleſhe, ſo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent wee are, ſo kay-colde and ſo ſlacke in our prayinge, that except we bee waked and ſtirred vp by the ſpirite of God, no man can pray aright, or as hee ſhould doe. Wee are ſo prone by nature to myſtruſtfulneſſe, diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, and fearefulneſſe, that wee dare not bee ſo bolde to call God <hi>Father,</hi> but by the motion of the ſame ſpirite. Hence commeth this godly carefulneſſe, hence this earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and vehemency, hence this chearefulnes, hence this truſt and confidence in obtayning our petitions, to conclude, hence commeth
<pb facs="tcp:26942:38"/>
theſe groninges that cannot bee expreſſed, whereof <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſpeaketh in the eyght to the <hi>Romaines</hi> verſe the twenty-ſixth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iudas</hi> teacheth not without cauſe, that no man can pray as hee ought, except he be directed by the ſpirite of God.</p>
            <p n="21">
               <hi>21. <hi>And kepe your ſelues in the loue of God, lookinge for the mercy of our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte vnto eternall lyfe.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he texte.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And keepe your ſelues in the loue of God] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Seeing charity is that Glue that ioyneth and giueth as it were together into one body,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulling.</note> and is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> temple of God, wherein hee deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, wee muſt take good heede that we ſticke together in mutuall charity one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and retaine our ſelues in the band of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and concorde:<note place="margin">A. Marlo.</note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> whereof much hath bene ſpoken in the thinges that went before. It followeth. <hi>Lookinge for the mercy of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> Becauſe many thinges doe intiſe vs to fall away from God,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> ſo that it is a very hard thinge for vs to bee kept ſounde and perfect to God to the ende, hee calleth backe the faithfull, to the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the laſt day. For the only looking for the ſame ought to ſtay vs vp, leaſt at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26942:38"/>
time wee ſhould deſpayre or waxe weary of our life: otherwiſe wee ſhould of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fainte euery moment.<note place="margin">M. Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>M.</hi> Here therefore is hope taught, and the croſſe commended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. For the whole raſe and courſe of our life ought ſo to bee framed and trayned vp, that wee ſhould doe nothing els but looke and waighte, and fight continually for the life to come. It followeth. <hi>Vnto eternall life] <hi>A.</hi>
               </hi> This is the ende and ſcope of all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and doinges.<note place="margin">A. Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> And here wee haue to note, that onely through the merites and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Chriſte, (and not for any workes of ours) <hi>Iudas</hi> would haue vs to looke and hope for the lyfe to come. For hee ſhall in ſuch wiſe be our Iudge, that hee will haue the free benefit of redemption purchaſed by him, for a rule to iudge by. <hi>A.</hi> Away therefore here,<note place="margin">Aug. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> with all mans merytes. <hi>For not of workes that bee in ryghteouſneſſe which wee haue done,</hi> (ſayth <hi>S. Paule</hi> in <hi>Tytus</hi> the thirde Chapter, verſe the fifth) <hi>but accordinge to his mercy Chryste hath ſaued vs. B.</hi> Therefore beholding this end,<note place="margin">Bulling.</note> let vs ſerue God in a true fayth, and in loue vnfayned.</p>
            <p n="22">
               <hi>22. <hi>And haue compaſſion of ſome,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The texte</note> 
               <hi>ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26942:39"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erus.</note>
               <hi>And haue compaſſion] <hi>I.</hi>
               </hi> After that <hi>Iudas</hi> had ſpoken many thinges concerninge theſe mockers &amp; ſeducers, now againe hee teacheth the faithfull, howe and after what ſorte they ought to behaue them ſelues, in correctinge and admoniſhing of their brethren, that they may bee brought backe agayne to the Lord: and that is after dyuers ſortes, according as euery mans nature is. For towards the meeke and gentle, and ſuch as are tractable and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be taught, wee muſt vſe gentleneſſe and lenity. But with thoſe that are obſtinate and ſtubburne,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug. Mar.</note> wee muſt deale more ſharply, to terrifie them and to feare them. <hi>A.</hi> This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t whereof mention was made afore. Firſt he deſcribeth and ſetteth forth the nature of charity,<note place="margin">M. Luth.</note> 
               <hi>M</hi> which is, to bee ſory &amp; grieued, to ſee certaine ſo miſerable, blinde, &amp; obſtinate, that they haue no care at all of their ſoule health.<note place="margin">A. Marlo.</note> 
               <hi>A.</hi> Charity ſurely coueteth to ſaue all: and therefore cannot chooſe but bee ſory for the deſtruction of myſerable men. Which thing wee may behold in men endued with great powre and holineſſe. For <hi>Samuell</hi> not without great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion lamented y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of <hi>Saule. 1.</hi> kings <hi>15.</hi> verſe <hi>35.</hi> and <hi>16.</hi> verſe <hi>1. Ieremy</hi> alſo moſt bitterly bewayled the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Hiëruſalem,</hi> Chap. <hi>9.</hi> verſe <hi>1. Paule</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26942:39"/>
wryteth to the <hi>Philippians</hi> after this ſorte. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny walke, of whom I haue tolde you often, &amp;c.</hi> Chap. <hi>3.</hi> verſe <hi>18.19.</hi> and in the <hi>2. Corinthians, 12.</hi> verſe <hi>20. I feare mee least when I come, I ſhall not finde you ſuch as I woulde, &amp;c.</hi> Our Sauiour Chriſte him ſelfe knowing perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the maliciouſneſſe and ingratitude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Iewes,</hi> drawing now neare towards <hi>Hië<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> could not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>hold him ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teares. <hi>Luke 19.</hi> verſe <hi>41.</hi> It followeth. <hi>Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating or putting difference] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> Some doe tranſlate it, <hi>When yee ſhall bee iudged.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bulling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>But whereas the participle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is doubtfull, the actiue ſignification doth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter agree with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> texte. If wee bee willing to help them that goe aſtray, the ſumme is this: wee muſt conſider euery mans nature: ſuch as are meeke, gentle &amp; tractable, muſt bee gently intreated to be brought into the right way, as worthy of mercy &amp; fauor. But if any man bee obſtinate or ſtubburne, hee muſt bee ſharply corrected. <hi>A.</hi> Some,<note place="margin">Aug. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> not vnfitly haue tourned this participle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hauing offended.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <hi>23. <hi>And other ſome ſaue with feare,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The text<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>pulling them out of the fire, hating euen the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſpotted by the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And other ſaue with feare] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> As if he ſhould ſay;<note place="margin">Bulling.</note> it is not enough for vs to lament &amp; bewaile
<pb facs="tcp:26942:40"/>
the miſerable eſtate of wicked men, vnleſſe alſo wee giue all dilygence and earneſt care to winne them to Chryſte by all meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, in whom there is ſome hope: eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſettinge before them the threatenings of Gods iudgements.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> But becauſe to much ſeuerity and ſharpneſſe in correcting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukinge, moſt commonly is odyous, <hi>Iude</hi> doth excuſe it by neceſſity, becauſe otherwiſe they cannot bee ſaued, vnleſſe they doe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and of their owne accorde follow that which is good. It followeth. <hi>Pulling them out of the fyre] <hi>M.</hi>
               </hi> Hee vſeth an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legant metaphor of fyre:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Luth.</note> for if wee bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſaue a man that is lyke to bee bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, wee doe not ſhewe him our finger, or nicely reache him our hande, but vyolently plucke him out with all ſpeede that may bee to ſaue his lyfe: ſo muſt they bee handled that haue no care of their ſoule, that will not come to God of their owne accorde vnleſſe they bee drawne with mighte and mayne.</p>
            <p>Here the manner of ſpeakinge is to bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this worde <hi>(ſauing)</hi> when it is apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto men: not that the ſeruantes of God are authors, but myniſters of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A. Marlo.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> So and in this ſence, theſe places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt bee taken: <hi>Take heede vnto thy
<pb facs="tcp:26942:40"/>
ſelfe, and vnto doctryne, and continue therein: For in ſo doing, thou ſhalt both ſaue thy ſelfe, and them that heare thee. Tymothe 1.</hi> the fourth Chapter, verſe the ſixteenth. Likewiſe <hi>Saint Iames</hi> in the fifte Chapter of his epiſtle, the <hi>19.</hi> and <hi>20.</hi> verſes. <hi>Brethren</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>if any of you doe erre from the truth, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conuert him, let the ſame knowe, that hee which conuerteth the ſinner from going aſtray out of the way, ſhall ſaue a ſoule from death, and ſhall hyde the multitude of ſinnes.</hi> It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. <hi>Hating euen the garment ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wyth the fleſh] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> This place,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> which otherwiſe would ſeeme obſcure and darke, will bee eaſie enough, if the metophor bee well and plainely declared. Hee would haue therefore the faythfull, not onely to bee free from all vice and corruption, but alſo hee doth admonyſh them to auoyde whatſoeuer is acceſſary thereunto, leaſt any infection ſhoulde take holde of them. As if wee ſhould haue an occaſion to ſpeake of diſhoneſty, wee will ſay that all inticementes, and prouoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to luſtfull deſires, muſt bee taken away. This will appeare more clearely, if the reſt of the ſentence bee ſupplied: that is: that wee muſt hate not onely the fleſh, but euen the very garment it ſelfe ſpotted by the fleſh, leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:26942:41"/>
wee bee defiled by the touching thereof. Much leſſe doth hee winke at wickedneſſe, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth rather that all occaſions and acceſſories thereunto, as they call it, may bee cleane cut of.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulling.</note> 
               <hi>B.</hi> Some will haue this to bee the ſence and meaning: I would not haue you to keepe too much familiarity wyth the wycked, but to ſhunne their company rather, not hating the perſon, but the wickedneſſe of the man. For it commeth oftentimes to paſſe that when they thinke them ſelues falſe enough and in good caſe, ſodainely through their own weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and imbecillity, they haue periſhed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether wyth them, to whom they haue beene helpfull. For the good oftentimes are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the badde. But the firſt expoſition is more true.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <note place="margin">The texte.</note>
               <hi>24. <hi>Vnto him that is able to keepe you free from ſinne, and to preſent you faultleſſe before the preſence of hys glorye wyth ioye,</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bulling.</note>
               <hi>Vnto him that is able to keepe you] <hi>B.</hi>
               </hi> This is the concluſion of the epiſtle gratulatory: wherein the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruant of Chriſte ſheweth, who it is that keepeth vs from ſinne, from whence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth all our powre &amp; ſtrength
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:26942:41"/>
in perſeuering in well doinge, from whence eternall lyfe, euen from God doe all theſe things come.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> for all our ſtudies and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are not auayleable, except the effect thereof come from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> powre of God:<note place="margin">A. Marl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>A</hi> which <hi>Paule</hi> in theſe wordes doth euidently declare in his ſecond epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Corinthians</hi> the third Chapter, verſe the fourth: <hi>Such truſt haue we through Chriſte to God warde, not that wee are ſufficient of our ſelues to thinke any thing as of our ſelues, but our ſufficiencie is of God.</hi> And in the ſecond Chap. of the epiſtle to the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> verſe thirteenth. <hi>It is God which worketh in you, both to will and to doe of good will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>C.</hi> Some bookes haue <hi>(them):</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluin.</note> if wee reade it ſo, then the meaning is: It is your partes and duety to indeuoure, that they may bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but it belongeth to God only to performe,<note place="margin">A. Marlo.</note> 
               <hi>A</hi> for ſo ſpeaketh hee by the Prophet. <hi>I, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen I,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>am the Lord, and beſide mee there is no other ſauiour. Eſay 43.</hi> verſe the eleuenth: and <hi>45.</hi> verſe the one and twentith. Agayne, <hi>I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the lande of Aegypt, and thou ſhalte knowe no God but mee onely, neyther is there any ſauyour beſides mee. Oſee</hi> thirteenth, verſe the fourth.<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> 
               <hi>C.</hi> Notwithſtanding to reade (you) and not (them) doth better agree with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> text,
<pb facs="tcp:26942:42"/>
for the alluding to the ſentence that went a litle before. For after that hee had exhorted the faythfull to ſaue that which was loſt, to the intent that hee may make them better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all their indeuours and laboures are in vayne, except God bee the worker: hee ſheweth that they cannot otherwiſe bee ſaued but by the powre of God. Howbeit in this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter member, the greeke worde is otherwyſe, namely, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifieth a garding or keeping. So hee ſhould haue a reſpect to the firſt member, when hee ſaith, keepe your ſelues. It followeth. <hi>And to preſent you faultleſſe before the preſence of his glory] <hi>A. Paule</hi>
               </hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. Mar.</note> that God hath choſen vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the foundation of the world was layde, that wee ſhould bee holy, and without blame before him through loue. <hi>Epheſians</hi> the firſte Chapter, verſe the fourth. But wee can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee founde to bee ſuch, vnleſſe God him ſelfe doe bring it to paſſe in vs. It followeth. <hi>Wyth ioy] <hi>I.</hi>
               </hi> Heere the faythfull ought to bee of good courage to perſeuere in well doing to the ende:<note place="margin">L. Pely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane.</note> As if hee ſhould ſay, you haue great cauſe to reioyce and to bee glad, for the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chryſte: when other that ſeeme heere to liue deliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſinne for a ſeaſon, ſhall mourne &amp; lament.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:26942:42"/>True ioy, the ioy that euery good chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man ought to haue, hath alwayes faith an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed and ioyned with it according to this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Peter:</hi> whom yee haue not ſeene (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge Chryſte) and yet loue him, in whom euen nowe though yee ſee him not, yet doe you beleeue him, &amp; reioyce with ioy vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and glorious, receauing the ende of your faith, euen the ſaluation of your ſoules. The firſt epiſtle of <hi>Peter,</hi> the firſt Chapter, verſe the eyght. Here the godly beginne their ioy, but when Chryſte commeth to his laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then it ſhall bee fully perfected and completed.</p>
            <p n="25">
               <hi>25. <hi>To God our ſauiour, which only is wiſe,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The texte.</note> 
               <hi>bee glory, and maieſty, and dominion, and powre, nowe and euer. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To God our ſauiour which onely is wiſe] <hi>C.</hi>
               </hi> All creatures doe giue all the prayſe and glory, of all wyſedome &amp; knowledge,<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> as moſt proper and peculiar to God alone: ſee the ſixeteenth chapter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Romaines,</hi> verſe twenti-ſeuenth.<note place="margin">Aug Mar.</note> 
               <hi>To God our ſauiour] <hi>A.</hi>
               </hi> Wee haue declared before in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twenty-fourth verſe, and proued out of the ſcriptures, that God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is both the author, and finiſher of our
<pb facs="tcp:26942:43"/>
ſaluation. It followeth. <hi>Bee glory, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, and dominion, and powre, now and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.]</hi> As wiſedome, ſo alſo to God only hee aſcribeth all glory, according to <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the firſt to <hi>Tymothe,</hi> the firſt Chapter, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>17.</hi> verſe. <hi>To the king euerlaſting, immortall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, vnto God onely wiſe bee honor and glory for euer and euer. Amen.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> in his <hi>104. Pſalme,</hi> the <hi>31.</hi> verſe. <hi>The gloryous maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of the Lorde ſhall indure for euer: the Lord ſhall reioyce in his workes.</hi> It followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now and for euer.]</hi> Although the name of God bee continually prophaned and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the wicked, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly doe euen now celebrate and ſet forth the glory and maieſty of the ſame: which is a ſacrifice moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto our God, as hee him ſelfe witneſſeth by his prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in the <hi>50. Pſalme,</hi> the <hi>23.</hi> verſe. <hi>Who ſo offereth mee thankes &amp; praiſe, hee honoreth mee: and to him that ordereth his conuerſation a ryghte, him wyll I ſhewe the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of God.</hi> This word <hi>(Amen)</hi> as it is vſuall and familiar both with Chriſte our Sauiour him ſelfe, with his Apoſtles, &amp; with all the holy men of God, ſo it confirmeth, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and ſealeth vp as it were, whatſoeuer thinges haue beene wrytten or ſpoken by the ſaintes and holy men of God, inſpired wyth
<pb facs="tcp:26942:43"/>
the holy-ghoſt: ſo that wee neede not doubt of their faith, truth, and verity, but cleaue conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, and ſticke faſt vnto them. The which thinge that wee may doe, God the Father of heauen grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto vs, who hath vouchedſafed to call vs into the fellowſhip of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte. <hi>B.</hi> To whom bee praiſe,<note place="margin">Bulling.</note> confeſſion, and thankes giuing worlde without ende. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <closer>Soli Deo honor, &amp; gloria. Amen.</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
